What is your analysis Sir, that the speed
आपका क्या एनालिसिस है सर कि जिस स्पीड से
and velocity and heat with which cinema was being consumed
और वेलोसिटी से और हीट से सिनेमा कंज्यूम
10-15 years ago at least
हो रहा था आज से 10-15 साल पहले एटलीस्ट
in theatres etc, what has happened to that
थिएटर्स एटसेट्रा में व्हाट हैज़ हैपेंड टू
magic, what do you think, what is your guess,
दैट मैजिक व्हाट डू यू थिंक व्हाट्स योर
see, the theatrical business has definitely reduced, there is no
गेस देखिए थिएटरिकल बिज़नेस कम तो हुआ है
doubt about it and I feel
हम इसमें कोई दो राय नहीं है अ और मुझे
sad because I am a theatre person,
अफसोस होता है क्योंकि मैं थिएटर का बंदा
my entire career is
हूं मैं मेरी पूरा पूरा करियर मेरा जो है
associated with cinema halls,
वो सिनेमा हॉल्स के साथ ही जुड़ा है जो
today I am sitting in front of you, whatever
मैं आज आपके सामने बैठा हूं जो कुछ मैंने
work I have done, it is
काम किया है वो
because of those cinema halls that I have
उस सिनेमाघरों की वजह से मैं यहां तक
reached here.  Well, my belief is complete
पहुंचा हूं। अ तो मेरा बिलीफ पूरा है
in theatres.  But I think there are two or three things.
सिनेमाघरों में। लेकिन मुझे दो-तीन चीजें
Firstly, we should
लगती हैं। एक तो ये कि हमने
look at the quality of films, I
देखिए क्वालिटी ऑफ़ फिल्म्स पे मैं बात
will not talk about this topic because the quality
नहीं करूंगा इस टॉपिक पे क्योंकि क्वालिटी
of films will become your colleagues.
ऑफ़ फिल्म्स आपके कलीग्स हो जाएंगे। आप
Why would you comment on that so much?  No no, that
क्यों उस पे कमेंट करोगे ज्यादा? नहीं
because that is a
नहीं उस उस क्योंकि वो तो एक
variable.  And that variable is always
वो एक वेरिएबल है। और वो वेरिएबल हमेशा
going to be there.  When you do a formula,
रहने वाला है। जब आप फार्मूला करते हो तो
how is the film with a variable in it like this is a variable?  It is good and it is bad.  So
फिल्म कैसी है? अच्छी है बुरी है। तो उसको
if we keep that aside, the quality of cinema is
अगर हम अलग रख रख दें क्वालिटी ऑफ़ सिनेमा
sometimes good and
क्योंकि वो कभी-कभी अच्छा होता है,
sometimes bad.  We
कभी-कभी बुरा होता है। हम लोग कभी-कभी
also go to circles sometimes.  There is a growth.
सर्कल्स में भी जाते हैं। एक ग्रोथ होता
Yes.
है। हां।
So that's a variable.  If we take it apart, then the
तो वो एक वेरिएबल है। उसको अगर अलग-अलग तो
constants which are a basic business
जो कांस्टेंट्स हैं जो एक बेसिक बिजनेस का
method, we follow them in a very strange manner.
एक तरीका होता है वो हम लोग काफी अजीब
So because of that, the
फॉलो करते हैं। तो लिहाजा उसकी वजह से भी
theatrical business has also reduced significantly.  Hmm.
बहुत कम हो गया है थिएटिकल बिजनेस। हम्।
Ah, we as a film industry have
अह हमने एज एन फिल्म इंडस्ट्री ही ऐसे कुछ
taken some steps which have caused losses to us.  The
कदम लिए हैं जिससे हमें खुद नुकसान हुआ
theatrical window that we have has become very
है। हम जैसे थिएटरिकल जो विंडो है वो बहुत
small.  It is obvious that if you
कम छोटी हो गई है। उससे जाहिर है अगर आप
can watch the movie at home then why would you
घर पे फिल्म देख सकें तो फिर आप क्यों
come to the theatre?  Right and that too without
थिएटर में आएंगे? राइट और वो भी बगैर कोई
paying any extra money.  Absolutely.  So then
एक्स्ट्रा पैसे दिए। बिल्कुल। तो फिर मतलब
what else should I say?  No sir I know I will
और क्या कहा जाए? नहीं सर मैं पता है आई
give you a young person's perspective.
विल गिव यू एक यंग पर्सन्स पर्सेक्टिव।
I meet a lot of people from your industry.
मैं आपके इंडस्ट्री से काफी लोगों से
Maybe, if I muster up the courage,
मिलता हूं। शायद जी अगर मैं हिम्मत करूं
our industry is common in a sense,
तो हमारी इंडस्ट्री कॉमन ही है एक सेंस
we are in the entertainment industry and I
में हम एंटरटेनमेंट इंडस्ट्री में और मेरे
feel that many times people do
को लगता है काफी बार लोगों को रियलाइज
not realise that it is a hardware thing,
नहीं होता कि ये ना इट्स अ हार्डवेयर थिंग
that the base of technology is hardware
कि ना देखो टेक्नोलॉजी का बेस हार्डवेयर
and when the hardware changes, the
रहता है और जब हार्डवेयर चेंज होता है तो
user behaviour changes.  Hmm
यूजर बिहेवियर चेंज हो जाता है। हम्म
hmm.  Now your movie or my podcast or
हम्म। अब आपकी मूवी या मेरा पडकास्ट या
my friend's story, whether it is a normal story.
मेरे दोस्त की कहानी चाहे वो नॉर्मल कहानी
It is coming with the worst of
हो। इट इज कमटिंग वि द वर्स्ट ऑफ
humanity swipe.  And that hardware is now in our
ह्यूमैनिटी स्वाइप। और वो हार्डवेयर अब
hands.  So it is not like I
हाथ पे है। तो ऐसा भी नहीं है कि मैं मूवी
want to watch a movie on my TV.  When
लगा के देखना चाहता हूं अपने टीवी पे। जब
I read 25,000 types of nonsense content it turns
मैं 25,000 टाइप का नॉनसेंस कंटेंट जो
my brain completely off.  I
मेरे दिमाग को बिल्कुल ऑफ कर देता है। हाथ
can see it on my hand.  So I do the same thing and go to the
पे देख सकता हूं। तो मैं वो सेम चीज जाके
cinema and drive the car.  I should buy a ticket worth ₹1000.
सिनेमा गाड़ी चलाऊं। ₹1000 की टिकट
For two people, there should be no one around who is
खरीदूं। दो लोगों के लिए आसपास कोई
misbehaving.  Should I take the tension about this thing from my wife?
बदतमीजी ना कर रहा हो। मेरी वाइफ से इस
And those factors
चीज़ की टेंशन लूं। एंड दोज़ फैक्टर्स
start coming into play.  I think
स्टार्ट कमिंग इन टू प्ले। मेरे को लगता
it's a hardware thing.  You're
है इट्स अ हार्डवेयर थिंग। आप उसके बाद
going straight to YouTube after that, right?  No, we're
सीधा YouTube पे जा रहे हो ना? नहीं, हम
just coming to the theatre.  After the theatre,
सिर्फ थिएटर में आ रहे हैं। थिएटर के बाद
nowhere, we are in the theatre.  Then we
कहीं नहीं हम थिएटर में हैं। फिर बाद आगे
will see what happens next.  First, we are just
देखेंगे क्या होना है। पहले हम सिर्फ
coming to the theatre.  Well you're just
थिएटर में आ रहे हैं। अच्छा आप सिर्फ
in the theater.  Yes.  Let's go.  Only
थिएटर में हो। जी। लेट्स गो। सिर्फ थिएटर
in theatres.  Full anxiety.  Full anxiety.  Full
में। फुल एंग्जायटी। फुल एंजाइट। फुल
anxiety.  Theatrical release is just full
एंग्जायटी। थिएटर वाला रिलीज सिर्फ तो फुल
anxiety.  Wow.  What does Aamir Khan's anxiety
एंजाइटटी। वाओ। व्हाट डस आमिर खान एंजाइटी
feel like?  What is it?  What are the thoughts
फील लाइक? व्हाट इज इट? व्हाट आर द थॉट्स
in your head?  It won't work.  This type
इन योर हेड? चलेगा नहीं चलेगा। दिस टाइप
of stuff?   A
ऑफ स्टफ?
yes, actually every film has a
अ हां सबसे तो एक्चुअली यह फिल्म हर फिल्म
different quality.
की अलग क्वालिटी होती है। इस ये फिल्म
I have specifically made this film because
मैंने खासतौर से इसलिए भी बनाई है क्योंकि
this is a very important topic for our
ये एक बहुत इंपॉर्टेंट टॉपिक है हमारे
society. We have neuro-divergence and
समाज के लिए हम न्यूरो डायवर्जेंस हम और
I feel that as people, sometimes we become very
मुझे लगता है कि एज अ हम लोग काफी कभी-कभी
insensitive.  Like who people who
इनसेंसिटिव हो जाते हैं। जैसे कि जो जो
people with ah ah mental disabilities
लोग पीपल विद अह अह मेंटल डिसेबिलिटीज़
okay.  I think this is the legal term for it
ओके। आई थिंक दिस इज़ द लीगल टर्म फॉर इट
in India.  Sure, there is a
इन इंडिया। श्योर अ
neurotypical person, just like the one we
एक होते हैं न्यूरोटिपिकल जैसे हम लोग
call normal is
नॉर्मल जिसको बोलते हैं वो न्यूरोटिपिकल
called neurotypical and neurodivergence means
कहलाते हैं और न्यूरोड डायवर्जन मतलब
those whose intellectually they are a little different,
जिनकी इंटेलेक्चुअली थोड़ी अलग है
intellectually they are a little different from us, right
इंटेलेक्चुअली वो थोड़े अलग हैं हमसे राइट
and so this is a topic on which I feel that
और तो ये एक टॉपिक है जो मुझे लगता है कि
we have never seen a film made on this on such a large scale on a public platform,
हमने ऑन अ पब्लिक प्लेटफार्म कभी ये इतनी
or as far as I remember, for me
है या जो मुझे या जो याद आ रहा है
this is not just a film.  There is the
तो मेरी मेरे लिए ये बहुत सिर्फ फिल्म
film
नहीं है। फिल्म तो है ही
but along with it the entire team has made
लेकिन उसके साथ-साथ द एंटायर टीम हैज़ मेड
this film because we want to sensitize
दिस फिल्म बिकॉज़ वी वांट टू सेंसिटाइज
people
पीपल
about this topic.  So, there is also anxiety about
अबाउट दिस टॉपिक। तो ए्जायटी ये भी रहती
whether it will reach everywhere or not.  Will this
है कि ये हर जगह पहुंचेगी कि नहीं। ये
film reach the hearts of the people or
फिल्म लोगों के दिलों तक पहुंचेगी कि
not?  Whatever we have done to
नहीं। जो हमने कोशिश की है लोगों को
sensitize people, have we done it right or
सेंसिटाइज करने के लिए वो हमने सही किया
not?  We see how much impact the
है कि नहीं। हम वो कितना असर छोड़ेगी
film will have on people.  That is one of the concerns
फिल्म लोगों पर। दैट इज वन ऑफ द कंसर्न्स
that you were asking about.  Right?  It's one
जो ए्जायटी आप पूछ रहे थे। राइट? इट्स वन
of them.  Is there a success failure anxiety
ऑफ़ देम। इज देयर अ सक्सेस फेलियर एंजाइटी
associated with it?  Yes, I definitely
एसोसिएटेड विद इट? जी हां, यकीनन मैं
want us to succeed without a doubt.
चाहता हूं कि अनडाउटेडली हम कामयाब हो।
I want people to like our film.
मैं चाहता हूं कि हमारी फिल्म पसंद आए
Yes.  Interesting.  The First
लोगों को। हां। इंटरेस्टिंग। द फर्स्ट
Movie That I Ever Cried In.  Hmm.  Ever were
मूवी दैट आई एवर क्राइड इन। हम्म। एवर वाज़
stars on the ground.  Ok.  And I Seven Six
तारे जमीन पर। ओके। और मैं सेवन सिक्स
is ​​a 2006 release Sir.  It's probably from 2007 or eight.
2006 की रिलीज़ है सर। 2007 या आठ की है
Okay sir anything you want me to pull
शायद। अच्छा सर एनीथिंग यू वांट मी टू पुल
up we have magic.  We can just pull up
अप हमारे पास जादू है। वी कैन जस्ट पुल अप
here and we can talk about it, right?  I
हियर एंड वी कैन टॉक अबाउट इट, है ना? आई
think it is from 2007, right?  Because I was in
थिंक 2007 की है ना? बिकॉज़ आई वाज़ इन
seventh grade.  And I remember that I did
सेवंथ ग्रेड। और मेरे को याद है मेरे को
n't even know that one could cry after watching a movie.  I
तो पता भी नहीं था कि मूवी देख के रो सकते
mean, what does a 10-11 year old child
हैं। मतलब आप 10- 11 साल के बच्चे को क्या
know?  And I remember watching it
पता होता है। एंड आई रिमेंबर वाचिंग इट
and crying.  And let's focus on the stars
एंड क्राइंग। एंड चलो टू फोकस ऑन तारे
on the ground.  Hmm hmm.  There's something about
जमीन पर। हम्म हम्म। देयर इज समथिंग अबाउट
a story that is so well told.  Hmm that goes
अ स्टोरी दैट इज सो वेल टोल्ड। हम्म कि वो
right through the heart.  Hum Hum and You
दिल को आरपार कर जाती है। हम हम एंड यू
have a history of giving cinema like that
हैव अ हिस्ट्री ऑफ गिविंग सिनेमा लाइक दैट
hmm all the way from Andaz Apna Apna but then but then also
हम्म ऑल द वे फ्रॉम अंदाज अपना-अपना बट
Lagaan you know what I am
देन बट देन आल्सो लगान यू नो व्हाट आई एम
talking about what is that what happens in a story
टॉकिंग अबाउट व्हाट इज दैट एक स्टोरी में
that touches the heart.   Hmm I
ऐसा क्या होता है जो दिल को छू जाता है।
wonder hmm see
हम आई वंडर
I believe that when the
देखिए मेरा यह मानना है कि जब
writing is good, hmm then no matter what
लिखाई अच्छी होती है ना हम्म तो चाहे जो
topic we make a film on, it touches the heart
भी टॉपिक पे हम फिल्म बनाएं वो दिल को छू
if the writing is good, hmm then
लेती है अगर लिखाई अच्छी हो हम्म तो
writing is very important, there is a structure for every film, is there
राइटिंग बड़ी इम्पोर्टेन्ट है हर फिल्म के
like this if
लिए कोई स्ट्रक्चर रहता है ऐसा इज देयर इफ
I am ever telling a story to my
आई एम एवर टेलिंग अ स्टोरी टू माई
friends, I need to remember something that's going to
फ्रेंड्स आई नीड टू रिमेंबर समथिंग दैट्स
help my story land better or if
गोइंग हेल्प माय स्टोरी लैंड बेटर ऑर इफ
I ever write a story well, for
आई एवर राइटिंग अ स्टोरी वेल वेल, फॉर
cinema, I can give you some basic
सिनेमा, आय कैन गिव यू अ फ्यू बेसिक
tips.  One thing is that premise is very
टिप्स। एक तो ये होता है कि प्रेमाइस बहुत
important.  You need to have a clear
जरूरी होता है। यू नीड टू हैव अ क्लियर
premise.
प्रेमाइस। कि आप जो कहानी कह रहे हैं वो
What are you trying to say with the story you're telling?  What do you want to say in one line
आप कहना क्या चाह रहे हैं? एक लाइन में आप
?  For example, if
क्या कहना चाह रहे हैं? जैसे दंगल का अगर
we take the example of Dangal, then the girls are less than the boys, that is
हम ले लें तो मारी छोरियां छोरों से कम है
the main thought of the film.
कि दिस इज़ द मेन थॉट ऑफ़ द फिल्म।
Brilliant.  Ok?  So you need a strong
ब्रिलियंट। ओके? सो यू नीड अ स्ट्रांग
premise
प्रेमाइस
and an affirmative premise.  It should be an arbitrary
एंड अफमेटिव प्रेमाइस। इट शुड बी अर्मेटिव
sentence
सेंटेंस
and there should be a clear premise and
और क्लियर प्रेमाइस होना चाहिए और उस पे
then the film is made on that premise.
फिर फिल्म बनती है प्रेमाइस पे।
Secondly, your goal setting should be done
दूसरा ये कि आपका जो गोल सेटिंग है वो
quickly.  At the beginning of the film,
जल्दी हो जाना चाहिए। फिल्म की शुरुआत में
you should tell the audience where the film is going.
ही आप ऑडियंस को बता दें कि ये कहां जा
Like
जैसे के
any revenge film, Yaadon Ki Baaraat
जैसे कोई रिवेंज फिल्म है, यादों की बारात
came a long time back in the 70s.  There are three brothers.   He
बहुत पहले 70ज में आई थी। तीन भाई हैं।
sees his parents getting murdered with his own eyes.  Then they get separated.  So
से देखते हैं। फिर बिछड़ जाते हैं। तो
as soon as that prog ended the kids got
जैसे ही वह प्रोग खत्म होता है कि बच्चे
separated.  The parents have been murdered.  So,
बिछड़ गए। मां-बाप का कत्ल हो चुका है। तो
we as an audience know where this film is
हम एज एन ऑडियंस हमको पता है कि ये फिल्म
going.  These three children will
कहां जा रही है। ये तीन बच्चे जो हैं ये
meet each other when they grow up, find each other
बड़े हो के मिलेंगे एक दूसरे को ढूंढ
and then take revenge from the villain.  So the
लेंगे और फिर विलेन से बदला लेंगे। सो द
goal is set very early in the film.
गोल इज सेट वेरी अर्ली इन द फिल्म। फिल्म
At the very beginning of the film, in the first 101%
के शुरुआत में ही पहले 101%
we understand where the story is
में हमको समझ में आ जाता है कि कहानी कहां
going.  In Lagaan, when Bhuvan says that the
जा रही है। लगान में जब भुवन बोलते हैं
condition is accepted.  We hope your goal is locked, I see,
शर्त मंजूर है। हम योर गोल इज लॉक्ड आई सी
so goal locking is an important aspect early enough
सो गोल लॉकिंग इज एनेंट एस्पेक्ट अर्ली
and then there are two-three things that the more
एंड फिर दो तीन चीजेंट है कि आप जितना
streamlined you keep the narrative, the character
स्ट्रीमलाइन रखो नैरेटिव को हम अ कैरेक्टर
development should be good, along with the main plot, the
डेवलपमेंट अच्छा हो हम अ जो मेन प्लॉट है
sub-plots should also be
उसके साथ-साथ सब प्लॉट्स भी हो
interesting.  And the resolution of
इंटरेस्टिंग। और जो रेजोल्यूशन है वो मैन
your sub-plots should end before the main plot ends.
प्लॉट खत्म होने से पहले आपके सब प्लॉटस
You should wind up the sub
खत्म हो जाने चाहिए। यू शुड वाइंड अप द सब
plots before the main plot.  Because once the
प्लॉट्स बिफोर द मेन प्लॉट। बिकॉज़ एक दफा
main goal is achieved, the public will
मेन गोल अचीव हो गया उसके बाद पब्लिक
not pay attention.  She will not pay attention.  The movie is
ध्यान नहीं देगी। ध्यान नहीं देगी। फिल्म
done for me.  Right right right.  This
हो चुकी है मेरे लिए। राइट राइट राइट। ये
remains an open loop.  There are some basic things.
खुला हुआ लूप रह गया। कुछ बेसिक चीजें
Yes.  Which has to be taken care of.
हैं। हां। जिसका ध्यान रखना पड़ता है। गजनी
Sir, in Ghazni, goal setting is a little late, isn't it?
में सर गोल सेटिंग थोड़ी लेट होती है ना?
Because first you are showing all this
बिकॉज़ फर्स्ट यू आर शोइंग ऑल दिस
happiness and it's all good.  No, no,
हैप्पीनेस एंड इट्स ऑल गुड। नहीं नहीं
no.  Good.  Ghajini starts
नहीं। अच्छा। गजनी तो शुरू होती है वो
in the present tense when you see that he
प्रेजेंट टेंस में जब आप देखते हैं कि वो
kills a man, right right right
किसी आदमी को मारता है वो राइट राइट राइट
right, then from there you are confused that he is not
राइट तो आप वहीं से कंफ्यूज हैं कि इसको
remembering anything, he is taking photos, I do
कुछ याद नहीं आ रहा है ये फोटो ले रहा है
n't know what he is doing, I get it but I get it
पता नहीं क्या-क्या कर रहा है आई गेट इट
you are right because
बट आई गेट इट यू आर राइट क्योंकि वो शुरू
in the beginning when it shows all that confusion jacked,
में व्हेन इट शोज़ ऑल दैट कन्फ्यूजन जैक्ड
means you all jacked and whatever that is the
मतलब यू ऑल जैक्ड एंड व्हाटएवर दैट्स द
moment you are already aware that something is going to happen
मोमेंट यू आर ऑलरेडी अवेयर कि कुछ होने
there is some strangeness about us or
वाला है देयर सम स्ट्रेंजनेस अबाउट टू अस
I C I C that's very interesting it is a
या आई सी आई सी दैट्स वैरी इंटरेस्टिंग एक
book of art and dramatic writing by the
किताब है आर्ट और ड्राैटिक राइटिंग बाय
writer, it is very difficult to name it, friend.
राइटर का नाम बहुत बड़ा मुश्किल है यार।
I always forget.  Sir I asked him will
मैं हमेशा भूल जाता हूं। सर उससे पूछा
he find Eugene or yes the
मैंने वो ढूंढेगा ना यूजीन या हां
Art of Dramatic Writing.  The Art of the
आर्ट ऑफ़ ड्रामेटिक राइटिंग। आर्ट ऑफ़ द
Art of Dramatic Writing,
आर्ट ऑफ़ ड्राैटिक राइटिंग
that book is very helpful.  Not just
तो वो किताब बड़ी हेल्पफुल है। ना सिर्फ
for theatre but for cinema.  It
थिएटर के लिए लेकिन सिनेमा के लिए। वो
was written for the theatre.  Yes it is.  Lajos
लिखी गई थी थिएटर के लिए। हां ये है। लाजो
Lajos Ergery.  Agri.  Agri Agri Yes, it
लाजोस एरर्गी। एग्री। एग्री एग्री हां,
is a very difficult name.  I can't pronounce it.
बड़ा मुश्किल नाम है। मुझसे प्रोनाउंस नहीं
Where is the treatment Agri bhai?  This
होता। कहां का है इलाज एग्री भाई? ये तो
is very interesting.  I don't know friend where are you from
बड़ा इंटरेस्टिंग है। आई डोंट नो यार कहां
?  This is good Hungarian.  is Hungarian.
का? ये अच्छा हंगेरियन है। हंगेरियन है।
Well very interesting.
अच्छा वैरी इंटरेस्टिंग।
1888 There's something about stories that are
1888 देयर आर समथिंग अबाउट स्टोरीज जो
so timeless that he writes the book in 1888.
इतना टाइमलेस रहती है कि वो 1888 में बुक
We read that book till today.
लिखता है। हम आज तक उस बुक को पढ़ते हैं।
Actually he has
एक्चुअली उसने पूरा एक उसका साइंस
made a whole lot of science writing, you know he is
राइटिंग का एक ही इज़ मेड यू नो ही इज़
actually broken down writing.  Hum and I
एक्चुअली ब्रोकन डाउन राइटिंग। हम एंड आई
think what he did is that he tried to,
थिंक व्हाट ही डड इज़ दैट ही ट्राइड टू
well this what he explains about writing, he
अच्छा यह जो वो समझाता है लिखाई के बारे
is talking about mainstream
में ही इज टॉकिंग अबाउट मेन स्ट्रीम
writing, otherwise you can write anyone, there are no
राइटिंग अदरवाइज यू कैन राइट एनी हाउ हम
rules in writing,
कोई रूल्स नहीं है राइटिंग में कोई रूल्स
you can write the way you want to, but
नहीं है आपको जैसे लिखना है लिखिए लेकिन
if you want more people to
अगर आप चाहते हैं कि ज्यादा लोग आपके
connect with your material, then he
मटेरियल से कनेक्ट हो तो फिर वो आपको
tells you that there are certain things which
बताता है कि कुछ चीजें हैं जो
psychologically keep people connected
साइकोलॉजिकली लोगों को जोड़ के रख जोड़ के
and from the research that he has done,
रखती हैं और वो उसने जो रिसर्च किया है
all these things have come out that the premise should be
उससे ये सारी चीजें निकली हैं कि प्रमाइस
clear, goal setting should be quick,
क्लियर होना चाहिए गोल सेटिंग जल्दी होनी
all this is interesting
चाहिए ये सब इंटरेस्टिंग
and sometimes we even break the rules of writing.
और कभी-कभी हम रूल भी तोड़ते हैं राइटिंग
But if you have understanding then you
का। लेकिन अगर आपको अंडरस्टैंडिंग है तो
yourself understand that I am breaking this rule
आप समझ आप खुद समझते हैं कि ये रूल मैं
and why I am breaking it.
तोड़ रहा हूं और क्यों तोड़ रहा हूं। कि
What is its pay off going to be?  Sometimes you have to
इसका पे ऑफ क्या होने वाला है। कभी-कभी आप
break the rules.  Hum but you should know why
रूल को आपको तोड़ना भी पड़ता है। हम बट यू
you are breaking the rules and what
शुड नो व्हाई यू आर ब्रेकिंग रूल एंड
you are going to do and you know why you are
व्हाट यू आर गोइंग टू एंड यू नो व्हाई यू
doing it.  I always say you are allowed to
आर डूइंग इट। आई ऑलवेज से यू आर अलाउड टू
break the rules once you are the master of it.
ब्रेक द रूल्स वंस यू आर द मास्टर ऑफ इट।
That it only comes as a function of now I am the
कि इट ओनली कम्स एज अ फंक्शन ऑफ नाउ आई एम
master of these rules.  Now I can break
द मास्टर ऑफ दीज रूल्स। नाउ आय कैन ब्रेक
it in style.  Now I can break it for
इट टू स्टाइल। नाउ आय कैन ब्रेक इट फॉर
function.  but before that if to to to to to to to to
फंक्शन। बट बिफोर दैट इफ टू टू टू टू टू
break the rules may be it will crumble
टू टू टू ब्रेक रूल्स मे बी इट विल क्रमबल
whatever the game might be we are I or there is
व्हाटएवर द गेम माइट बी हम आई या
truth in what you are saying
उसमें जो आप कह रहे हैं उसमें सच्चाई तो
but I don't think that I am a master
है बट मुझे लगता नहीं कि मैं मास्टर
we all are students let me
मास्टर हूं हम सब स्टूडेंट्स हैं मैं आपको
tell you we are all students yes
बता दूं हम सब स्टूडेंट्स हां किसी भी
in any field we all keep learning always
फील्ड में हम सब हमेशा सीखते रहते हैं
sure but to what extent sir
श्योर जी बट टू व्हाट एवर एक्सटेंड सर ये
you can take this compliment that you know you have
तो आप ले ही सकते हो कॉम्प्लीमेंट दैट यू
done fantastic work the country
नो यू हैव डन फैंटास्टिक वर्क द कंट्री
loves you you made cinema I have very rarely
लव्स यू यू मेड सिनेमा आई हैव वेरी रेयरली
connected with cinema cinema is not my
कनेक्टेड विद सिनेमा सिनेमा इज नॉट माय
strength hmmm hmm the only person I am
स्ट्रेंथ हूं हम्म हम द ओनली पर्सन आई एम
just the only person like I said I studied
जस्ट द ओनली पर्सन लाइक आई सेड मैं पढ़ाई
when I did it with three deeds cadet the
जब करी आई डिड इट विद थ्री डीड्स कैडिट द
first film I cried in was Tare Zameen Par
फर्स्ट फिल्म आई क्राइड इन वास तारे जमीन
Satyamev Jayate gave me my moral fabric I was
पर सत्यमेव जयते गव मी माय मोरल फैब्रिक
right at that as also when
मैं आई वास राइट एट दैट एज आल्सो जब
Satyamev Jayate is airing I am like 14
सत्यमेव जयते एयर हो रहा है आई एम लाइक 14
15 like those issues were oh my god and you
15 लाइक दोज़ इश्यूज वर ओह माय गॉड एंड यू
know I no  Yesterday I was sitting and thinking that forget
नो मैं ना कल बैठ के सोच रहा था कि फोरगेट
the podcast if I just talking to Aamir sir what I am going to ask when I
द पडकास्ट इफ आई जस्ट टॉकिंग टू आमिर सर
wanted to really ask you this do you think all like
वांटेड टू रियली आस्क यू दिस डू यू थिंक
what do you think is arts
ऑल ऑल लाइक व्हाट डू यू थिंक इज आर्ट्स
responsibility?  You feel there
रिस्पांसिबिलिटी? आपको लगता है कि आर्ट
is a need for art because you
में देयर इज अ नीड फॉर देयर टू बिकॉज़ यू
do a lot of social messaging.  Yes.  Look,
डू अ लॉट ऑफ़ सोशल मैसेजिंग। जी। देखिए
I think I am talking about cinema.
मुझे ये लगता है कि मैं सिनेमा की बात कर
Talking about cinema, yes
रहा हूं। सिनेमा की बात हां
I think the primary and fundamental
मुझे लगता है कि द प्राइमरी और फंडामेंटल
responsibility of an entertainer
रिस्पांसिबिलिटी ऑफ़ एन एंटरटेनर
in cinema is to entertain.
इन सिनेमा इज़ टू एंटरटेन।
If you want sociology lessons you
अगर आपको सोशियोलॉजी का लेसन चाहिए तो आप
go to college.  You have come to the cinema hall, so
कॉलेज जाएंगे। आप सिनेमा हॉल आए हैं हम तो
obviously you want entertainment.  Yes.  So that
जाहिर है आपको मनोरंजन चाहिए। जी। सो दैट
I am sharply aware of that my primary
आई एम शार्पली अवेयर ऑफ दैट माय प्राइमरी
responsibilities are to entertain.
रिस्पांसिबिलिटीज टू एंटरटेन।
But I also feel that every profession
बट मुझे यह भी लगता है कि हर प्रोफेशन जो
contributes something or the other to the society.
है समाज में कुछ ना कुछ कंट्रीब्यूट करता
Just like
जैसे
doctors give us health, they give us health.   A
डॉक्टर्स हेल्थ हमें हमें हेल्थ देते हैं।
People who are in the police force maintain law and
अ जो लोग पुलिस फोर्स में हैं वो लॉ एंड
order.  Provides security.
ऑर्डर देते हैं। सिक्योरिटी देते हैं।
Provides security.  Our soldiers
सिक्योरिटी देते हैं। जो हमारे जवान हैं
keep us safe.  Every profession
वो हमको सेफ रखते हैं। हर प्रोफेशन जो है
contributes something or the other to the society.
सोसाइटी को भी कुछ ना कुछ कंट्रीब्यूट
[Music] The
[संगीत]
judiciary is what delivers justice.  So
जुडिशरी जो है वह जस्टिस देती है। तो
what is the contribution of a creative person
एक क्रिएटिव इंसान का क्या कंट्रीब्यूशन
to the society?  So I think that it is definitely
है समाज में? तो मुझे लगता है कि यकीनन
a huge responsibility to entertain people.
लोगों का दिल बहलाना एक बहुत बड़ी
But along with that there is
जिम्मेदारी होती है। लेकिन उसके साथ-साथ
another responsibility if we
भी एक जिम्मेदारी और है अगर हम वो
want to take that responsibility.  It is up to you and
जिम्मेदारी लेना चाहें तो। वो आपके ऊपर है
us and it is our responsibility that actually you
हम और वो यह जिम्मेदारी है कि एक्चुअली यू
can contribute to reach the hearts of the people.  You
आप लोगों के दिल तक पहुंच सकते हैं। आप
can gauge their emotions.  You
उनके जज्बातों को टटोल सकते हैं। आप
can make them think.  So I
उन्हें सोचने पर मजबूर कर सकते हैं। तो आई
feel that the job of an artist is not just to
फील दैट द जॉब ऑफ एन आर्टिस्ट इज़ नॉट जस्ट
entertain.  Yes, that is the main job.  But at the
टू एंटरटेन। यस, दैट इज़ द मेन जॉब। बट
same time it is also the job of an
उसके साथ-साथ इट इज़ आल्सो द जॉब ऑफ एन
artist.  When I say artist, I am
आर्टिस्ट। व्हेन आई से आर्टिस्ट आई एम
including painters, poets, writers, all
इंक्लूडिंग पेंटर, पोएट्स, राइटर्स सारे
fine arts, whoever is in whichever field,
फाइन आर्ट्स सब जो भी जिस फील्ड में भी
in the artistic field, in a way
हैं आर्टिस्टिक फील्ड में तो आपका एक तरह
you bring grace to the society, we, you
यू ब्रिंग ग्रेस टू सोसाइटी हम यू
inspire people, you can if you want to and
इंस्पायर पीपल यू कैन इफ यू वांट टू एंड अ
in this, there is a huge contribution towards nation building.
इसमें नेशन बिल्डिंग का बहुत बड़ा
Because a nation is
कंट्रीब्यूशन होता है। क्योंकि नेशन जो
not built with buildings.
बिल्ड होता है वो इमारतों से नहीं होता।
It happens to people.
वो लोगों से होता है।
And when you influence young minds in the right way,
और जब आप यंग माइंड्स को सही इनफ्लुएंस
then you are
करते हैं तो फिर आप एक पूरे जनरेशन को एक
able to give the right direction to an entire generation.  I remember when I was growing up, the
सही दिशा दे पाते हैं। मुझे याद है जब मैं
books I read had a
बड़ा हो रहा था तो जो किताबें मैंने पढ़ी
very profound impact on me.  The
हैं उनका बहुत गहरा असर हुआ है मुझ पे। जो
songs which I have heard, which have been our lyricists
मैंने गाने सुने हैं जो हमारे लिरिक राइटर
in India, Neeraj ji, Shailendra
रहे हैं हिंदुस्तान में नीरज जी शैलेंद्र
ji, Majroo sahab, all of them, Sahir sahab, they
जी मजरू साहब सारे जो साहिर साहब इन सबकी
say so much in their poetry, it makes
पोएट्री में इतना इतना कुछ कह जाते हैं ये
you think, it makes you feel, it makes you realize so many
दे मेक यू थिंक दे मेक यू फील दे मेक यू
things, that are all part of
रियलाइज सो मेनी थिंग्स दैट्स ऑल पार्ट ऑफ
building you, it builds us, we
बिल्डिंग यू हम इट बिल्ड्स अस हम एक कमाल
listen to amazing poetry, we listen to Kabir's couplet,
की पोएट्री सुनते हैं हम कबीर का दोहा
it affects us 100%, we
सुनते हैं उसका असर होता है हम पर 100% हम
see a painting, it affects us,
एक पेंटिंग देखते हैं उसका असर होता है हम
we read a story, it affects
पर हम कोई कहानी पढ़ते हैं उसका असर होता
us.  So actually
है हम पर। तो एक्चुअली
if you mean if one of the things that
अगर आपको अगर मतलब इफ वन ऑफ़ द थिंग्स दैट
a creative person can also do other than
अ क्रिएटिव पर्सन कैन आल्सो डू अदर देन
just entertain people is to bring grace to
जस्ट एंटरटेन पीपल इज टू ब्रिंग ग्रेस टू
society is to inspire people is to give
सोसाइटी इज टू इंस्पायर पीपल इज टू गिव
hope to people very interesting.  Or I
होप टू पीपल वेरी इंटरेस्टिंग। या आई
actually think the
एक्चुअली थिंक जो हमारी इंडियन लैंग्वेजेज़
potential of poetry in our Indian languages.  Yes sir, that means of
में पोएट्री की क्षमता है। जी सर मतलब ऑफ़
course I speak only English, otherwise but I do
कोर्स आई स्पीक ओनली इंग्लिश अदरवाइज बट
n't have that in English.  Like I,
आई आई इंग्लिश में वो नहीं है। लाइक मैं
Harivansh, probably grew up reading Bachchan ji's Madhushala,
हरिवंश शायद बच्चन जी की मधुशाला पढ़ते
Kabir's couplets, or the qawwalis
हुए बड़ा हुआ कबीर के दोहे चाहे नुसरत
sung by Nusrat Fateh Ali Khan, whoever has
फतेह अली खान ने जो कवालियां गाई वो किसी
written them, yes yes sir, what do you
ने भी लिखी हो पीछे जी जी सर क्या आप
say and when you are saying
बातें कर जाते हैं एंड व्हेन यू आर से
poets are amazing, poets are amazing, you
पोएट्स आर अमेजिंग पोएट्स आर अमेजिंग वो
say such a big thing in two lines that it takes a
दो लाइन में इतनी बड़ी बात कह जाते हैं कि
person 8-10-10 years to have that
मतलब 8-आ 10-10 साल तो आदमी को वो
breakdown.  You keep
ब्रेकडाउन करने में लग जाते हैं। आप सोच
thinking that
सोचते रहते हैं उसके मेरी मधुशाला की कॉपी
I have folded everything in my copy of Madhushala and that
में पूरी सब जगह मैंने ना वो फोल्ड कर रखा
it has to be rewritten again.  This is the
है कि इसको दोबारा रीजिट करना है। ये पूरी
wisdom of the whole life in four lines.
लाइफ का ज्ञान है चार लाइनों में है।
We are very next level, we but I think a
हम बहुत नेक्स्ट लेवल हम बट आई थिंक एक
very unique aspect that cinema has
बहुत यूनिक एस्पेक्ट जो सिनेमा के पास है
in India is entering people's living room
इंडिया में इज एंटरिंग पीपल्स लिविंग रूम
conversations, we said dyslexia,
कन्वर्सेशंस हम आपने डिस्लेक्सिया बोला
stars on the earth, we whole India knows
तारे जमीन पर हम पूरे इंडिया को पता है
what dyslexia is, and I will give
डिस्लेक्सिया क्या है हम एंड आई विल गिव
you a trivial example, hmm, one of you comes up
यू अ ट्रिविल एग्जांपल हम्म वन ऑफ यू कम्स
with six pack abs, before that there
अप विद सिक्स पैक एब्स उससे पहले इंडिया
is no concept in India sir, of six packs,
कोई कांसेप्ट नहीं है सर सिक्स पैक्स का
suddenly six pack abs thing, you come out with
सडनली सिक्स पैक एब्स थिंग यू कम आउट विद
eight pack abs, now eight pack are a thing, then
एइट पैक एब्स नाउ एइट पैक आर थिंग देन
people start wondering 12 bhi hote hain, like what should we do
पीपल स्टार्ट वंडरिंग 12 भी होते है क्या
now, stick to it and so there is a there is
लाइक अब क्या करें चिपका एंड सो देयर इज अ
an influential power in cinema.
देयर इज़ अ इन्फ्लुएंशियल पावर इन सिनेमा।
Cinema is a very secular medium that everybody
सिनेमा इज़ अ वैरी सेकुलर मीडियम इन दैट
consumes.  The entire country
एवरीबडी कंज्यूम्स। द एंटायर कंट्री
consumes it.  And once a film crosses a
कंज्यूम्स इट। एंड वंस अ फिल्म क्रॉसेस अ
certain threshold the entire world
सर्टन थ्रेशहोल्ड द एंटायर वर्ल्ड
consumes it.  And you are able to insert
कंस्यूम्स इट। एंड यू आर एबल टू इंसर्ट
through entertainment a small thought which you should
थ्रू एंटरटेनमेंट एक वो पतला सा ख्याल जो
remember.  Hmm weather that is excellence.   That was
याद रख लेना। हम्म वेदर दैट इज एक्सीलेंस।
the lesson I learnt in 3 Idiots.  Chess
थ्री इडियट्स में दैट वाज़ द लेसन आई। चेस
Excellence.  Chess Excellence.  Success will come
एक्सीलेंस। चेस एक्सीलेंस। सक्सेस आएगी झक
chasing you.  That was the message that you will
मार के पीछे। दैट वाज़ द मैसेज कि तू
chase excellence and success will follow you
एक्सीलेंस चेस का सक्सेस तेरे पीछे झक मार
while he is shaving and waving.
के जब वो शेविंग- वेविंग कर रहे होते हैं।
Correct.  And you are right.  I mean, I probably
करेक्ट। एंड यू आर राइट। मतलब मैंने शायद
undervalued these in my early life and
काफी अंडरवैल्यू किया अपनी अर्ली लाइफ में
what impact they could have?  Hmm but
इन कि क्या इंपैक्ट हो सकता है? हम्म बट
now in this moment when I look back and see
नाउ इन दिस मोमेंट व्हेन आई लुक बैक एंड
what three things did for me in my college
व्हाट थ्री डिड्स डिड फॉर मी इन माय कॉलेज
career and how it has all come through.  I am
करियर एंड हाउ इट हैज़ फॉललोड थ्रू। आई एम
multidisciplinary.  I have read more books
मल्टीडिसिप्लिनरी। आई हैव रड मोर बुक्स
and I can remember.  I have rented more
एंड आई कैन रिमेंबर। आई हैव रेंट मोर
scientific papers that I can remember.  I
साइंटिफिक पेपर्स दैट आई कैन रिमेंबर। आई
have written more than I can remember.
हैव रिटन मोर देन आई कैन रिमेंबर।
Purely because somebody said to me to
प्युअरली बिकॉज़ समबडी सेड टू मी एक्सीलेंस
chase excellence.  And that has currency.  That has
चेस कर। एंड दैट हैज़ करेंसी। दैट हैज़
value.  Hum that's what I think or I
वैल्यू। हम दैट्स व्हाट आई थिंक या या आई
think it is also an additional challenge.  An
थिंक इट इज आल्सो एन एडिशनल चैलेंज। एक
artist takes it, I will
आर्टिस्ट लेता है जो कि मैं यार इसमें ना
also do a messaging in it.  Because I
एक मैसेजिंग भी करूंगा। क्योंकि मैं हंसा
can leave you laughing.  Yes yes yes I
के छोड़ सकता हूं। जी जी जी मैं ठिठला के
can let it go with a chuckle.  Yes.  So I think when a
छोड़ सकता हूं। हां। तो आई थिंक जब एक ऐसी
script comes which is well written which
स्क्रिप्ट सामने आती है जो अच्छी भी लिखी
entertains you also.  It is also
हुई है व्हिच एंटरटेन्स यू आल्सो। इट इज़
saying something different then I get
आल्सो सेइंग समथिंग वेरीेंट देन आई गेट
very attracted to these kind of
वेरी अट्रैक्टेड टू दीज़ काइंड ऑफ़
scripts.  Hmm.  This story is also good.   It is
स्क्रिप्ट्स। हम्म। यह कहानी भी अच्छी है।
entertaining us, but it is
हमारा मनोरंजन भी कर रही है, लेकिन हमको
also giving us a lot.  In view of that,
बहुत कुछ दे भी रही है। इन व्यू ऑफ़ दैट,
how do you think of Bhagi's
हाउ डू यू यू यू यू यू यू थिंक ऑफ़ भागी के
Bose name?
बोस के नाम?
I don't think Delhi Belly had any special social
आई डोंट थिंक दिल्ली बेली का कुछ खास सोशल
message.  It was sir.  There was a message about tasty food.
मैसेज था। सर था। टेस्टी खाने को लेके
This was the message that you will get laxatives.
मैसेजिंग था। जुलाब लग जाएंगे ये मैसेजिंग
You are forgetting.  He had only one message.
थी। आप भूल रहे हो। उसका एक ही मैसेज था।
She it happens.
शी इट हपेंस।
Yes, right.  There was only one message from Delhi, Valley.
यस, राइट। दिल्ली, वैली का एक ही मैसेज
Damn that movie sir, I have shown the pictures to so many white people that I should
था। डैम दैट मूवी मे सर मैंने कितने गोरों
explain to you where I am from.  Come sit.  That
समझाता हूं मैं हूं कहां से। आओ बैठो। दैट
Movie Became a Cultural Bridge Today.  Yes yes.  Wow
मूवी बीम अ कल्चरल ब्रिज टुडे। जी जी। वाओ
what a film.  That movie and its opening was
व्हाट अ फिल्म। वो मूवी और उसकी ओपनिंग
such a bold movie,
इतनी बोल्ड मूवी रही वो
in the beginning, in the world, when the
शुरू में वो दुनिया में जब वो स्टार्ट
song starts, it is something like this.  Right?  It's
होता है गाना ऐसा ही कुछ ना। राइट? इट्स
[ __ ] beautiful.  Cycle Blues.  yes right right.
ब्यूटीफुल। साइकल ब्लूस। हां राइट
Tell me the story of your favorite childhood
टेल मी द स्टोरी ऑफ़ योर फेवरेट चाइल्डहुड
memory.
मेमोरी।
o
ओ
Favorite childhood memory.  Take a second.   I have
फेवरेट चाइल्डहुड मेमोरी। टेक अ सेकंड।
many childhood memories.
चाइल्डहुड मेमोरीज तो बहुत हैं।
What do you remember most fondly?
व्हाट डू यू रिमेंबर मोस्ट फोंडली?
Some birthday party, some friend hang out.
सम बर्थडे पार्टी, सम फ्रेंड हैंग आउट।
Ah hum I
अह हम
spent a lot of time with my mother
आई स्पेंड अ लॉट ऑफ़ टाइम विद माय मदर
growing up.
ग्रोइंग अप।
yes what was that like
हां
lovely she is a very
व्हाट वास दैट लाइक लवली शी इज़ अ वै
wonderful warm soft hearted person she is
वंडरफुल वार्म सॉफ्ट हार्टेड पर्सन शी
ranging from all of us to multiple
वैयरिंग हम हम सब में मल्टीपल
intelligences and it is not necessary to be
इंटेलिजेंससेस होती हैं और जरूरी नहीं कि
in reading and writing for some of them
रीडिंग एंड राइटिंग मे बी फॉर सम ऑफ़ देम
you could be a good orator you could be the speciality of Ammi is
यू कुड बी अ गुड ओरेटर यू कुड बी अम्मी की
that she is a very caring
खासियत ये है कि शी इज़ अ वैरी केयरिंग
person.  She has an intelligence of
पर्सन। शी हैज़ अ इंटेलिजेंस ऑफ
picking up that dude this guy is
पिकिंग अप दैट यार इस आदमी को इस चीज से
feeling really bad about this thing.  She can sense very
बुरी बुरा लग रहा है। शी कैन सेंस वेरी
fast that a person is not feeling good.  And
फास्ट दैट अ पर्सन इज नॉट फीलिंग गुड। एंड
she is very caring.  So that's something I
शी इज़ वेरी केयरिंग। सो दैट समथिंग आई
picked up from her.  What would you do with
पिक्ड अप फ्रॉम हर। व्हाट वुड यू डू विथ
her in your childhood?  Like how would you
हर इन योर चाइल्डहुड? लाइक हाउ वुड यू
spend time?  What stories did you hear from
स्पेंडिंग टाइम? आप क्या कहानियां सुनते
him?
थे उनसे?
No, I should just hang on with her.  Well,
नहीं, आई शुड जस्ट हैंग ऑन विथ हर। अच्छा,
a lot of times.  She would be doing some housework
अ लॉट ऑफ़ टाइम्स। वो घर का काम कर रही
or some work of her own.
होती थी या कुछ अपना काम कर रही होती थी।
You just hang out.  Hey, even when she went shopping
यू जस्ट हैंग आउट। अरे, वह शॉपिंग भी जाती
, she used to take us along.  We used to get
थी, तो हमको साथ में लेके चलती थी। हम लोग
very excited during shopping time.  Yes, I
बहुत पकते थे शॉपिंग के टाइम पे। हां, आई
am sure.  But they lived together.  So I have
एम श्योर। लेकिन साथ में रहते थे। सो आई
spent a lot of time with me growing
हैव स्पेंड अ लॉट ऑफ़ टाइम विद मी ग्रोइंग
up.  One of the worst memories of my
अप। वन ऑफ द वर्स्ट मेमोरीज ऑफ़ माई
childhood is going shopping with my mother.
चाइल्डहुड इज़ गोइंग शॉपिंग विथ माई मर।
Because I'm standing there friend finish it now.
क्योंकि मैं वहां खड़ा हूं यार अब खत्म
what are you buying?  I am
करो। क्या खरीद रहे हो? मेरे को तो समझ चल
already understanding it.  It's been 2 hours, it's been 3 hours, it's still going on.
ही रहा है। 2 घंटे हो गए, 3 घंटे हो गए चल
Right?  And some of my best
ही रहा है। राइट? एंड सम ऑफ़ माय बेस्ट
childhood memories are when I was three, four, five
चाइल्डहुड मेमोरीज आर जब मैं तीन चार पांच
years old and when I used to go to sleep, my
साल का था मैं सोने लगता था ना तो मेरे
father used to
पापा मेरे को पंचतंत्र से महाभारत से
narrate stories to me from Panchatantra, Mahabharata, Ramayana every day
रामायण से स्टोरी सुनाया करते थे एवरीडे
and he would fall asleep while narrating and
एंड वो सुनाते सुनाते खुद सो जाते थे और
we would also fall asleep while listening to it. Hmm but
सुनते-सुनते हम भी सो जाते थे हम्म बट
again, the foundation that those stories created,
अगेन वो स्टोरीज ने जो फाउंडेशन क्रिएट
a moral fabric, an
किया ना एक मोरल फैब्रिक क्रिएट किया एक
ethical fabric was created, that was very
एथिकल फैब्रिक क्रिएट किया वो बहुत
impactful. And the memory or I also love
इम्पेक्टफुल था एंड मेमोरी या आई आल्सो लव
stories, when I was a kid, I used to love listening to
स्टोरीज व्हेन आ किड आई टू लव लिसनिंग टू
stories,
स्टोरीज
so
तो
when our cook was done with dinner, she would
हमारी जो कुक थी वो उनका जब डिनर हो जाता
tell us some stories, she told the story of Sheikh Chilli,
जाते थे कुछ कहानी सुनाई शेख चिल्ली की
yes, then there used to be the Hawa Mahal programme on the
कहानी सुनाई हां फिर हवा महल प्रोग्राम
radio, well, you heard about Hawa
आता था अच्छा रेडियो पे अच्छा सुना आपने
Mahal, it comes even today, you can listen to it,
हवा महल अरे आज भी आता है सुन सकते हैं
yes, what happens in it, there is a radio spot of
हां क्या होता है उसमें रेडियो प्लेस हैं
10-15 minutes, okay, the spot is proper, like
10-15 मिनट के अच्छा ओके प्लेस हैं प्रॉपर
audio, yes, then
लाइक ऑडियो हां तो फिर
because Abba Jaan was a film producer, so
क्योंकि अब्बा जान फिल्म प्रोड्यूसर थे तो
many writers, directors used to come to our house to
बहुत राइटर्स डायरेक्टर्स घर पे आते थे
narrate stories to
कहानी सुनाने के
Abba Jaan. I
अब्बा जान को हम तो मुझे क्योंकि कहानियां
loved stories very much, so I used to sit in a corner.  I used to sit and
बहुत पसंद थी तो मैं कोने में बैठ के
listen from the age of five or six
सुनता था फ्रॉम द एज ऑफ़ फाइव और सिक्स
years old, so I think from that age
इयर्स ओल्ड तो आई थिंक उस उम्र से लेके 16
till the age of 16, 17, 18, when I became an assistant
17 18 बरस की उम्र तक जब मैं असिस्टेंट बन
and started working,
गया और काम करने लगा सैकड़ों कहानियां
I have heard hundreds of stories at home with Abba Jaan.
सुनी है मैंने घर पे अब्बा जान के साथ
I did not know at that time that I would
मुझे पता नहीं था कि उस वक्त के मैं
enter films, actually my
फिल्मों में आऊंगा हम तो एक्चुअली वो मेरा
Gurukul style training was going on, which I, when I did not know,
गुरुकुल स्टाइल ट्रेनिंग चल रहा था व्हिच
yes I did not know that
आई व्हिच आई डिडट नो हां आई डिडट नो दैट
time, I had never even thought at that
टाइम मैंने कभी सोचा सोचा भी नहीं था उस
time that I would enter films.  But today
वक्त कि मैं फिल्मों में आऊंगा। लेकिन आज
when I think about it, actually that was my
जब मैं सोचता हूं तो एक्चुअली दैट वाज़ माय
training ground as the films were being made around us
ट्रेनिंग ग्राउंड जो हमारे आसपास फिल्में
and we were watching them.  Right?  But sir
बन रही थी और हम देख रहे थे। राइट? बट सर
how can this happen?  Like I mean I'm
ऐसा कैसे हो सकता है? लाइक आई मीन आई एम
too young to know but cinema cinema is happening around you.
टू यंग टू नो बट आपके आसपास सिनेमा सिनेमा
You are living in Bombay.  You are
हो रहा है। आप बॉम्बे रह रहे हो। यू आर
part of a solid
पार्ट ऑफ अ सॉलिड
let's say solid film family.  I don't want to,
लेटस से सॉलिड फिल्म फॅमिली। आई डोंट वांट
your father was a producer you said.  My
टू योर फादर वाज़ अ प्रोड्यूसर यू सेड। माय
father was a producer.  Right!  Is that what it is now it
फादर वाज़ अ प्रोड्यूसर। राइट! इज दैट इज
is a natural consequence of
दैट नाउ इट इज अ नेचुरल कॉन्सक्वेंस ऑफ़
things now if my father was a
थिंग्स नाउ अगर इफ माय फादर वाज़ अ
producer most likely I would be
प्रोड्यूसर मोस्ट लाइकली आई वुड बी
acting it just begs the future to happen
एक्टिंग इट जस्ट बेग्स द फ्यूचर टू हैपन
then would you be considering an alternate career
तो आप वर यू कंसीडरिंग एन अल्टरनेट करियर
at some point no no I had never thought about it
एट सम पॉइंट नहीं नहीं मैंने तो सोचा ही
but actually this is not a thing of now, this has been happening
नहीं था पर एक्चुअली ये अब की बात नहीं ये
since before which it is very natural for
पहले से बात है जो इट्स वैरी नेचुरल फॉर
children to take on what their parents are
चिल्ड्रन टू टेक ऑन व्हाट देयर पेरेंट्स
doing because you see that going on around you,
आर डूइंग बिकॉज़ आप देखते हैं आपके आसपास
a lot of kids and up
वो चल रहा है तो अ लॉट ऑफ़ किड्स एंड अप
doing what their fathers, parents are
डूइंग व्हाट देयर फादर्स पेरेंट्स आर
doing it is a very natural process
डूइंग इट्स अ वैरी नेचुरल प्रोसेस
but I had never thought that I was
बट मैंने कभी सोचा नहीं था मैं स्पोर्ट्स
very interested in sports.  So I wanted to be a
में बहुत मेरी दिलचस्पी थी। तो आई वांटेड
sports person.  How would you
टू बी अ स्पोर्ट्स पर्सन। हाउ वुड यू
play?  Cricket?  I used to play cricket,
प्ले? क्रिकेट? आई यूज्ड टू प्ले क्रिकेट,
all racket games, tennis, adl.  TT.  Adele has just
ऑल रैकेट गेम, टेनिस, एडल। टीटी। एडल तो
arrived.  I am just joking,
अब आया है। आई एम जस्ट जोकिंग या तो अ खेल
I was very interested in sports and I had
कूद में बहुत रुचि थी मेरी और मैंने सोचा
never thought about what I should do in life.  Yes.
नहीं था कि मैं लाइफ में क्या करूं। हां।
But when there were holidays after 10th
लेकिन जब 10वीं के बाद जब छुट्टियां होती
, at that time I had a friend named Aditya
हैं, तो उस वक्त मेरा एक दोस्त था आदित्य
Bhattacharya.  Good.
भट्टाचार्य। अच्छा। बासु भट्टाचार्य के
Aditya Bhattacharya is the son of Basu Bhattacharya.
बेटे हैं आदित्य भट्टाचार्य
Basuda was a film maker. Aditya
अ बासुदा वास अ फिल्म मेकर हम तो आदित्य
wanted to make a student film
चाह रहा था कि वो एक स्टूडेंट फिल्म बनाए
and he asked for my help. I said I will
और उसने मेरी मदद मांगी आई सेड आई विल
help you, so we guys said, I was helping him.
हेल्प यू तो हम लोग ने आई वास हेल्पिंग
We made the film during the
हिम बेसिकली क्लासमेट्स थे हम तो 10थ के
holidays after the 10th board exams.
बोर्ड एग्जाम्स के बाद जो छुट्टियां होती
He
हैं उसमें हमने वो फिल्म बनाई उसने
directed it, I helped him. There were
डायरेक्ट की मैंने उसकी मदद की सारे
only two of us in all the departments. We were doing everything. So
डिपार्टमेंट्स हम दो ही लोग थे हम लोग सब
my experience of that one month was
मेरा वो एक महीने का
so much that I enjoyed doing that work that I
इतना मुझे मजा आया वो काम करके कि मुझे
felt, yes this is this world, I want to
लगा हां ये ये दुनिया है मुझे इस दुनिया
live in this world, the world of stories.  So
में रहना है कहानियों की दुनिया में। सो
I was around 16 and so when I first
आई वाज अराउंड 16 और सो व्हेन आई फर्स्ट
decided I want to be in the films very
डिसाइडेड आई वांट टू बी इन द फिल्म्स वैरी
interesting yes is this that this is Aditya
इंटरेस्टिंग हां इज दिस दैट ये आदित्य है
yes this is Aditya this is Aditya you are still
हां ये आदित्य दिस इज आदित्य यू आर स्टिल
friends I am assuming ya we are still
फ्रेंड्स आई एम असूमिंग या या वी आर स्टिल
friends wow so this man gives you the sort
फ्रेंड्स वाओ सो दिस मैन गिव यू द सॉर्ट
of impulse once inside I leave you
ऑफ़ इंपिटस एक बार अंदर आपको छोड़ दिया कि
wondering how the picture looks like yes the
देख पिचरे कैसी लगती है हां फिल्मों में
fun of working in films, the madness
काम करने का जो एक मजा होता है वो पागलपन
that happens, I experienced that
जो होता है वो एक्सपीरियंस मैंने किया
first hand when I worked with Aditya
फर्स्ट हैंड जब मैंने आदित्य के साथ काम
in his first film his first
किया उसकी पहली फिल्म फिल्म में उसकी पहली
film was called Paronoya.  It
फिल्म का नाम था पैरोनोया। इंटरेस्टिंग
was an interesting short film of 40 minutes.  And there were no
शार्ट फिल्म थी 40 मिनट की। और उसमें कोई
dialogues in it.  There was no background music
डायलॉग्स नहीं थे। कोई बैकग्राउंड म्यूजिक
, no sound effects, nothing.  There
नहीं था, कोई साउंड इफेक्ट्स नहीं थे, कुछ
was no soundtrack.  ok so i
नहीं था। साउंड ट्रैक ही नहीं था। अच्छा
mean that is just visual.  Good.  Just
तो मतलब वो जस्ट विजुअल। अच्छा। जस्ट
Visual.  And awkward silence.  Meaning hissing
विजुअल। एंड ऑकवर्ड साइलेंस। मतलब हिसिंग
silence, just there was silence in the entire theatre.
साइलेंस, जस्ट पूरे थिएटर में सन्नाटा
Only some visuals are running on the screen.
होता था। सिर्फ स्क्रीन पे कुछ विजुअल्स
And those visuals are some what
चल रहा है। और वो विजुअल्स आर सम वॉट ये
psychological paranoia style that
साइकोलॉजिकल पैरानोया स्टाइल में कि कुछ
means man it was about a boy growing up.
मतलब आदमी इट वाज़ अबाउट अ बॉय ग्रोइंग अप।
He is a 16 year old boy, what is
16 साल का लड़का है वो किस तरह व्हाट इज
his reaction to experiencing violence
हिस रिएक्शन टू एक्सपीरियंसिंग वायलेंस
for the first time, it is interesting.  What is
फॉर द फर्स्ट टाइम इंटरेस्टिंग। व्हाट इज
his reaction to his parents?  Hmm what
हि रिएक्शन टू हिस पेरेंट्स? हम्म व्हाट
is his reaction to his first case
इज हिस रिएक्शन टू हिज फर्स्ट केस
what is his reaction to him you know
व्हाट इज हिज रिएक्शन टू हिज़ यू नो
getting physical for the first time with his
गेटिंग फिजिकल फॉर द फर्स्ट टाइम विथ हिस
girlfriend.  So the
गर्लफ्रेंड। तो एक उस उम्र के लड़के की
experiences or psyche of a boy of that age and how he is you
एक्सपीरियंसेस या साइकी एंड हाउ ही इज यू
know so it was a
नो
kind of a slice of different
सो इट वाज़ अ काइंड ऑफ़ अ स्लाइस ऑफ़ डिफरेंट
emotions.  It wasn't really a linear
इमोशंस। इट वाज़ंट रियली अ लीनियर
script and you knew there was a specific plot
स्क्रिप्ट और यू नो विथ अ स्पेसिफिक प्लॉट
in it.  It was not like that.  Hum more a collection of
इन इट। ऐसा नहीं था। हम मोर अ कलेक्शन ऑफ़
scenes.  I mean, my guess is that you are
सीन्स। आई मेरे को माय गेस इज़ कि यू आर
probably closer to your mother when you
प्रोबेब्ली क्लोज़र टू योर मदर व्हेन यू
grow up?  Yes.  Who hit you more
ग्रोइंग अप? यस। आपको मारा किसने ज्यादा
?  Aunty did it, uncle did it or not,
है? आंटी ने किया अंकल ने या नहीं
father did it.  Well yes Bajan did.  How many
अब्बाजान ने। अच्छा हां बजान ने। कितनी
times would he have hit you?  Meaning was it frequent?
बार मारा होगा? मतलब वाज़ इट फ्रीक्वेंट?
But I don't know.
बट आई डोंट नो।
It's a beau question.  I am sorry.  I am
इट्स अ ब्यू क्वेश्चन। आई एम सॉरी। आई एम
sorry.  No, it was not that frequent.
सॉरी। नहीं इतना फ्रीक्वेंट भी नहीं था।
We have been beaten up a couple of times.  Once or
एक आध दफा हम लोगों को मार पड़ी है। एक आध
twice.  Yes.  Did you have fun like this?  You
दफा। हां। क्या मस्ती करते थे ऐसी? आप बस
were just young.  We used to keep doing some fun or the other.
छोटे थे। कुछ ना कुछ मस्ती करते रहते थे।
Faisal and I were both brothers.  They
फैसल और मैं हम लोग दोनों भाई थे। अलग
used to fight separately.  This or that.  And
झगड़ा करते रहते थे। ये वो कुछ। तो और
Abba Jaan's hand was quite heavy as well.  Every
अब्बा जान का हाथ काफी भारी भी था। हर
Baba, that, that's print also used to come.  Then the
बाबा वो वो उसका प्रिंट भी आता था। फिर
next day when he had to go to school, everything was visible to him that
अगले दिन स्कूल जाना है तो सब नजर आता था
he was studying.
कि उसको पड़ी है भाई।
My Baba has probably slapped me a total of
मेरे बाबा ने मेरे को टोटल शायद लाइफ में
three times in my life.  But it's been 30 years.
तीन बार थप्पड़ मारा है। बट 30 साल हो गए।
He has counted 30 years.  do you remember
30 साल गिनाया है उन्होंने। तेरे को याद
?  I beat you once.  do you
है? एक बार मैंने तेरी पिटाई करी थी। तेरे
remember?  Oh brother, the man feels so bad.
को याद है? ओ भाई आदमी को इतना बुरा लगता
But yes,
है। बट हां
in retrospect it seems right.
इन रेट्रोस्पेक्ट ठीक लगता है।
Not so bad in retrospect.
रेट्रोस्पेक्ट में इतना बुरा नहीं है।
Tell me about this idea
टेल मी अबाउट दिस आईडिया
of ​​perfect?  What do you think of perfect
ऑफ परफेक्ट? व्हाट डू यू थिंक ऑफ परफेक्ट
or that level of perfectionism got associated
या परफेक्शनिज़्म दैट लेवल गॉट एसोसिएटेड
with you for quite a bit.  What do you think
विद यू फॉर क्वाइट अ बिट। व्हाट यू थिंक
of that label?  Start with the idea.  What
ऑफ़ दैट लेबल? स्टार्ट विथ द आईडिया। व्हाट
is perfection to you?  I think there is no such
इज परफेक्शन टू यू? आई थिंक क्रिएटिविटी
thing as perfection in creativity
में परफेक्शन जैसी कोई चीज होती नहीं है
because every person has his own point of view.   There is no
क्योंकि हर आदमी का अपना नजरिया होता है।
one way to do anything.
कोई एक तरीका होता नहीं कोई भी चीज करने
So it's there is no perfect way of
के लिए। सो इट्स देयर इज़ नो परफेक्ट वे ऑफ़
doing anything in the creative world.
डूइंग एनीथिंग इन इन द क्रिएटिव वर्ल्ड।
Hmm
हम्म
so I don't believe in perfection.  I believe
तो आई डोंट बिलीव इन परफेक्शन। आई बिलीव
in magic.  More from us?  So when we are
इन मैजिक। हम से मोर? तो जब हम कुछ भी कोई
doing any scene or trying to capture any moment, does
सीन कर रहे हैं या कोई मोमेंट कैप्चर करना
magic happen in it or not?  Did we get something which was
मैजिक हुआ कि नहीं? डीड वी गेट समथिंग
really special.  Which may have
व्हिच वास रियली स्पेशल। व्हिच मे हैव
happened my mistake also.  So but I am
हैपन माय मिस्टेक आल्सो। सो बट आई एम
looking for magic.  Not Perfection and
लुकिंग फॉर मैजिक। नॉट परफेक्शन एंड हाउ
How Do You Get a Sense of
डू यू यू यू यू यू यू यू गेट अ सेंस ऑफ़
Magic?  you just watch it and you you you you you
मैजिक? यू जस्ट वाच इट एंड यू यू यू यू यू
know it and is it there?  You come to know you
यू यू नो इट और इज़ देयर? यू कम टू नो यू
feel it.  Ok.  What do you think of that whole
फील इट। ओके। व्हाट यू थिंक ऑफ दैट होल
media labeling that happened around you?
मीडिया लेबलिंग दैट हैपेंड अराउंड यू?
Mr. Perfect.  Mr. Perfectionist
मिस्टर परफेक्ट। मिस्टर परफेक्शनिस्ट
something of that nature?  Yes.  That labelling,
समथिंग ऑफ़ दैट नेचर? हां। वो लेबलिंग
actually, I do
एक्चुअली
n't know, that labelling happened some 15-20 years ago.
पता नहीं कुछ एक 15 20 साल पहले वो
Right.
लेबलिंग हुई थी। राइट।
I think my films were running one after the other.
आई थिंक मेरी फिल्में एक के बाद एक चल रही
So I think the media didn’t know
थी। तो आई थिंक मीडिया को समझ में नहीं
what to do?  What to do?  Yes.  No
आया कि क्या करें? क्या करें? हां। नहीं
not because
नॉट कि इसको बिकॉज़
he thought this is perfect.
तो उन्होंने उनको लगा यार ये परफेक्ट है।
This is called perfectionism.  So there I got that
इसको परफेक्शनिस्ट बोलते हैं। तो दे आई
label perfectionist.  But
गॉट दैट लेबल परफेक्शनिस्ट। बट हालांकि
nothing is perfect in creativity.
क्रिएटिविटी में कुछ होता नहीं है परफेक्ट
Hmm it is different.  Every man does his own thing.
है। हम्म अलग होता है। हर आदमी अपना अलग
Sure.  But it was also because you are
करता है। श्योर। बट इट वाज़ आल्सो बिकॉज़ आप
very hyperfocused on one movie in a year,
बहुत हाइपरफोकस्ड एक मूवी एक साल में
something of that nature was also part of
समथिंग ऑफ़ दैट नेचर वाज़ आल्सो पार्ट ऑफ़
your repeat war at that time that I
योर रेपिट वार ना उस टाइम पे कि मैं बहुत
would do very focused work.  From Lagaan to Lagaan, I have
फोकस्ड काम करूंगा। लगान से लगान तक मैंने
done more than one film at a time
एक वक्त पे एक से ज्यादा फिल्में की हैं
because that was how people worked in those days
क्योंकि उस वक्त लोग ऐसे ही काम करते थे
and for many years, I have been trying to
और मैंने कई सालों से मैं कोशिश कर रहा था
do only one film at a time.
कि हम एक वक्त पे सिर्फ एक फिल्म करें।
But my producers and directors were
लेकिन मेरे प्रोड्यूसर्स डायरेक्टर्स उसके
not ready for that.  Then when I
लिए तैयार नहीं थे। फिर लगान जब मैंने
produced Lagaan, I said that at this
प्रोड्यूस की तो फिर मैंने कहा कि भ ये इस
time we will do only one film.  And
वक्त हम सिर्फ एक ही फिल्म करेंगे। और तब
from then till now, by and large, I have done only
से लेके अब तक मैंने बाय एंड लार्ज एक
one film at a time.  Hmm what was
वक्त पे एक ही फिल्म की है। हम्म ऐसा क्या
so unique about Lagaan in that it was
व्हाट वास सो यूनिक अबाउट लगान इन दैट इट
made by you I was a producer so I could
मेड यू आई वास अ प्रोड्यूसर ना सो आई कुड
decide how it would be made
डिसाइड आई कुड डिसाइड कि कैसे बनेगी राइट
right so I said I will do the sing sound, I will do it
राइट तो मैंने कहा सिंग साउंड करेंगे एक
in one schedule, I will bring in the first AD system,
शेड्यूल में करेंगे फर्स्ट एडी सिस्टम में
so these were not the things that I
लाऊंगा तो ये सारी चीजें नहीं थी जो मैं
wanted to do, so as a producer
करना चाह रहा था तो एज अ प्रोड्यूसर जब
when I started as a producer,
मैं एज अ प्रोड्यूसर जब मैंने शुरुआत की
I included all these things in
तो मैंने ये सारी चीजें इंक्लूड की है
my film, I heard I have heard this, I do
मेरे फिल्म के अंदर आई हर्ड आई हैव हर्ड
n't understand that much what is
दिस मेरे को इतना समझ नहीं आता व्हाट इज
this unique first AD thing that you brought for
ये यूनिक फर्स्ट एडी थिंग जो आप लेके आए
Lagaan oh I know it's a little bit like
लगान ओ आई नो इट्स अ लिटल बिट ऑफ़ लाइक
you created that sort of position in
आपने यू क्रिएटेड दैट सॉर्ट ऑफ़ पोजीशन इन
the modern cinema, Hindi cinema ecosystem
द मॉडर्न सिनेमा हिंदी सिनेमा इकोसिस्टम
what is so unique about this first AD
व्हाट इज सो यूनिक अबाउट दिस फर्स्ट एडी
position and what is this exactly, it
पोजीशन और ये होती क्या है एक्साक्ट्ली इट
just makes it, it's
जस्ट मेक इट इट
a very organised way of working, there's a
इट्स अ वैरी ऑर्गेनाइज्ड वे ऑफ़ वर्किंग
lot of paper work in it, so there are
उसमें पेपर वर्क काफी होता है तो कोई
less mistakes because things are
गलतियां कम होती हैं बिकॉज़ थिंग्स आर
planned well and advanced and the first AD is the
प्लंड वेल एंड एडवांस और फर्स्ट एडी जो
centre of influence.  And
होता है वो सेंटर ऑफ़ इनफेशन होता है। एंड
he and she controls set.
ही और शी कंट्रोल्स सेट।
So how much time will it take for prep?
तो प्रेप के वक्त भी कितना वक्त लगेगा?
It's so he's the First AD, he's a person who's
इट्स सो ही इज़ फर्स्ट एडी इज़ अ पर्सन हु
not actually a creative person.  Hmm he is an
इज नॉट एक्चुअली अ क्रिएटिव पर्सन। हम्म
administrative person.  So it is
ही इज़ एन एडमिनिस्ट्रेटिव पर्सन। तो सिर्फ
his only responsibility to ensure that the work
उसकी जिम्मेदारी है कि काम जो है स्मूथली
goes on smoothly and the schedule that I have made as a
जाए और जो शेड्यूल मैंने बनाया है एज़ अ
First AD is followed.  We should not
फर्स्ट एडी वो फॉलो फॉलो हो। वी शुड नॉट
go, we should not fall behind schedule.  And things should
गो, वी शुड नॉट फॉल बिहाइंड शेड्यूल। एंड
happen in time.  So, the First AD
थिंग शुड हैपन इन टाइम। सो, द फर्स्ट एडी
is not really concerned with how well you are
इज़ नॉट रियली कंसर्न विथ हाउ वेल यू आर
making the film.  Hum,
मेकिंग द फिल्म। हम्,
he is concerned with whether you are doing it in
ही इज कंसर्नड विद वेदर यू आर डूइंग इट इन
time or not.  Got it.  Hum and because he is
टाइम ऑर नॉट। गॉट इट। हम् एंड बिकॉज़ ही इज़
a centre of information he and she, so he is
अ सेंटर ऑफ़ इनफार्मेशन ही और शी, तो वो ही
the one who
इज़ द वन हु
gives that information out to different
गिव्स दैट इनफार्मेशन आउट टू डिफरेंट
departments so that they can
डिपार्टमेंट्स ताकि वह सिंक्रोनाइज होके
work in synchronization.  Because we have so many
काम करें। क्योंकि हम लोग इतने
departments working together.  So, there
डिपार्टमेंट साथ में काम कर रहे हैं। सो,
has to be someone's synchronicity.  Yes.  So that is the
देनी टू बी समवन सिंक्रोनसिटी। यस। तो वो
responsibility of the First ED.  So that was
फर्स्ट ईडी की जिम्मेदारी होती है। तो
n’t there earlier.  I used to be the chief assistant.
पहले वो नहीं था। हम लोग चीफ असिस्टेंट
Why did he exactly not do the paper work at that time?  As an
पेपर वर्क क्यों नहीं करते थे? एज एन
assistant when I first worked.
असिस्टेंट जब मैं पहली दफा मैंने काम
I was 18 when I started with Zara.
किया। मैं 18 साल का था जरा के साथ मैंने
So the shooting of the film had started.
शुरू किया। तो फिल्म की शूटिंग शुरू हो
I join you a little late.  So I
चुकी थी। आई जॉइ लिटिल लेट। तो मैंने चीफ
asked the Chief Assistant, have you guys completed this paper work?  Let
असिस्टेंट से पूछा कि भ इस पेपर वर्क आप
me just see.  So he
लोग कर चुके हैं। मैं जरा देखूं। तो उसने
said which paperwork?
कहा कौन सा पेपरवर्क?
So, you must have done something like location breakdown, actor
तो ऐसे मतलब लोकेशन ब्रेकाउन, एक्टर
requirements, property requirements,
रिक्वायरमेंट, प्रॉपर्टी रिक्वायरमेंट्स,
costume requirements.
कॉस्ट्यूम रिक्वायरमेंट्स कुछ तो किया
Not only this, we know all this here.
होगा आपने। ही से नहीं वो सब हमको यहां
So I said, well
तो आई सेड अच्छा
then mistakes happen.  Now tell me, I will
तो फिर गलतियां होती हैं। अब बताओ मैं
write it.  Yes.  Yes.  Then you start
लिखता हूं। हां। हां। देन यू स्टार्ट
making mistakes.  You know when you don't do
मेकिंग मिस्टेक्स। यू नो व्हेन यू डोंट अह
the paper work properly.
डू द पेपर वर्क प्रोपर्ली।
So when you do this systematically,
तो ये जब आप सिस्टमेटिकली करते हैं तो
mistakes are reduced.  It is not that it does not
गलतियां कम होती हैं। ऐसे नहीं कि नहीं
happen, it happens less.  The chances of these things
होती कम होती हैं। चांसेस ऑफ इट थिंग्स
going wrong is less is reduced.  So it
गोइंग रोंगों इज लेस इज रिड्यूस्ड। सो
's a very planned way of working which I thought is
इट्स अ वैरी प्लंड वे ऑफ़ वर्किंग व्हिच आई
nice.  So we should bring it in
थॉट इज़ नाइस। सो वी शुड ब्रिंग इट इन
interesting.  I have a question.  We are What Are
इंटरेस्टिंग। आई हैव अ क्वेश्चन। हम व्हाट
You Self-Conscious About Even Now?  Well,
आर यू सेल्फ कॉन्शियस अबाउट इवन नाउ? वैसे
we are self-conscious about many things.
सेल्फ कॉन्शियस तो हम लोग बहुत सारी चीजों
Like when in PK
के साथ होते हैं। लाइक जब अह पीके में जब
I had to do that scene when I
मुझे वो सीन करना था जब एस अ एलियन में
come as an alien.  There would be clothes.  Yes.  I was
आता हूं। कपड़े होते। हां। आई वाज
conscious.  I was definitely self-
कॉन्शियस। आई वाज डेफिनेटली सेल्फ
conscious.  Right.  So yes.  But like but you
कॉन्शियस। राइट। तो हां। बट लाइक बट यू
deal with it.  That's my job, man.  I had to do that scene.
डील इट। वह अपना काम है यार। वो सीन करना
I am playing a character.  Which
था मुझे। आई एम प्लेइंग अ कैरेक्टर। जिसका
we have used in this film also.
इस्तेमाल हमने इस फिल्म में भी किया है।
Good.  He is a basketball coach.   There's a
अच्छा। ही इज़ अ बास्केटबॉल कोच।
basketball coach and he's Tingu.  Everyone
बास्केटबॉल कोच है और वो टिंगू है। सब
calls him Tingu.  Good.  So you play
उसको टिंगू बोलते हैं। अच्छा। सो यू प्ले
to the insecure.  Or he is very insecure
टू द इनसिक्योर। या ही इज़ वैरी इनसिक्योर
about his height.  He doesn’t have to listen to it.
अबाउट हिज हाइट। उसको सुनना नहीं है। उसको
He feels very bad when someone calls him Tingu.  Very
टिंगू बोले बड़ा उसको बुरा लगता है। वैरी
self conscious about his height.  Yes.  So that was one
सेल्फ कॉन्शियस अबाउट हिज हाइट। हां। तो
thing I was self conscious about
दैट वाज़ वन थिंग आई वाज़ सेल्फ कॉन्शियस
earlier when I
अबाउट अर्लियर
started out as an actor isn't it funny that
व्हेन आई स्टार्टेड आउट एस एन एक्टर इजंट
a lot of very successful people are shorter I don't think about their
इट फनी दैट अ लॉट ऑफ वेरी सक्सेसफुल पीपल
height
आर शॉटर आई डोंट थिंक के हाइट से कुछ मतलब
I don't think so but sir I mean if you feel
आई डोंट थिंक सो बट सर मतलब अगर इफ यू फील
wait I think people think that I'm shorter than
वेट मेरे को लोग ऐसा सोचते हैं दैट आई एम
you try harder in the world
शॉर्टर देन यू ट्राई हार्डर इन द वर्ल्ड
to achieve things you you you you you you think that
टू अचीव थिंग्स यू यू यू यू यू यू यू थिंक
loop exists that does I suppose that does
दैट लूप एक्सिस्ट दैट डज आई सपोज़ दैट डज़
you see what research finds
आप देखिए आप क्या रिसर्च में क्या मिलता
but that could play a factor sure hmm
है बट दैट कुड प्ले एन फैक्टर श्योर हम्म
and there was a lot I know many you know taller
एंड वास देयर अ लॉट आई नो मेनी यू नो टॉलर
people who are successful and very
पीपल हु आर वै सक्सेसफुल एंड वेरी
talented and what is your height I will
टैलेंटेड एंड आपकी हाइट क्या है आई विल
take the compliment sir you say no problem yes
टेक द कॉम्प्लीमेंट सर आप बोल दो कोई बात
yes right right right right right
नहीं यस हां राइट राइट राइट राइट राइट
interesting but this is what happens when
इंटरेस्टिंग बट ये होता है कि जब आप बचपन
you are
में जब आप
struggling with something in your childhood for
किसी चीज से जूझ रहे होते हो हम फॉर
example if you are dyslexic and you
एग्जांपल अगर आप डिस्लेक्सिक हो और आप
see in school that yaar  People are understanding but
स्कूल में देख रहे हो कि यार लोग समझ रहे
I am not able to understand.
हैं मैं नहीं समझ पा रहा हूं।
So that does drive you to work harder perhaps but that can also depress you it can also
सो दैट डस ड्राइव यू टू वर्क हार्डर
dishearten you and it can also
कैन आल्सो डिसहार्टेन यू एंड इट कैन आल्सो
drive you to work harder it can both
ड्राइव यू टू वर्क हार्डर इट कैन बोथ
things can happen but I think you are right about one thing
थिंग्स कैन हैपन बट आई थिंक यू आर राइट
in childhood when you face
अबाउट वन थिंग इन चाइल्डहुड व्हेन यू फेस
challenges it kind of brings out the fight
चैलेंजेस इट काइंड ऑफ ब्रिंग्स आउट द फाइट
in you it creates character it creates
इन यू इट क्रिएट्स कैरेक्टर इट क्रिएट्स
character fire yes it creates fire a
कैरेक्टर फायर हां क्रिएट्स फायर मैं एक
hunger is created in me sir all the injuries are a
भूख पैदा होती है सर सारी चोटें मोटिवेशन
source of motivation I tell my audience to
का सोर्स है मैं तो अपनी ऑडियंस को कहता
remember that you should
हूं याद रखना जितनी चोटें लगी है उनको
not suppress all the injuries you have suffered.  They have to be channeled.  You will understand in a year and a half or two
दबाना नहीं है। उनको चैनल करना है। डेढ़ दो
how to run a channel.  Right now is the
साल में समझ आएगा चैनल कैसे करना है। अभी
point of grieving.  Grieve your grief.
तो ग्रीविंग का पॉइंट है। ग्रीविंग ग्रीव
When eventually it does become
कर लो। जब वो इवेंचुअली व्हेन इट डस बिकम
energy there is nothing like a good injury.
एनर्जी देयर इज़ नथिंग लाइक अ गुड इंजरी।
Hum Hum
हम हम
All greatness becomes begins after a great
ऑल ग्रेटनेस बिकम बिगिंस आफ्टर अ ग्रेट
failure.  I think that's very
फेलियर। आई थिंक दैट्स वैरी
well my failures have been my biggest
वेल माय फेलियर्स हैव बीन माय बिगेस्ट
teachers for sure.  Right?
टीचर्स फॉर श्योर। राइट?
The most I have learned is from my failures.
सबसे ज्यादा मैंने सीखा है मेरी नाकामी।
My failures have taught me the most.  What do
माय फेलियर्स हैव टॉट मी द मोस्ट। व्हाट
you think is the film that audiences will
डू यू थिंक इज द फिल्म दैट ऑडियंसेस विल
remember the longest from you?  Hmm from
रिमेंबर द लॉन्गेस्ट फ्रॉम यू? हम्म फ्रॉम
my films?  Yes.
माय फिल्म्स? यस।
Oh I don't know.  Take a guess.  I will
ओह आई डोंट नो। टेक अ गेस। आई विल
actually ask taare zameen par.  Tare zameen par
एक्चुअली आस्क तारे जमीन पर। तारे जमीन पर
wood you think for me I think it.  Three
वुड यू थिंक फॉर मी आई थिंक इट्स। थ्री
dears 3 yes three idiots.  But this is the 3D generation
डियर्स 3 यस थ्री इयडिस। बट ये 3D जनरेशन
sir.  These are under 25 children.  They do
है ना सर। ये अंडर 25 बच्चे हैं। इनकी
n't have much history, no life,
ज्यादा हिस्ट्री नहीं है लाइफ नहीं वैसे
actually Andaz Apna Apna also I think
एक्चुअली अंदाजा अपना-अपना आल्सो आई थिंक
just me that's all I was waiting for
बस मैं बस दैट्स ऑल आई वाज वेटिंग फॉर
let's say it game over because ah my favourite is
लेट्स से इट गेम ओवर बिकॉज़ ah माय फेवरेट
Andaz hum my favourite it's a mad film
इज़ अंदाजा हम माय फेवरेट इट्स अ मैड फिल्म
totally madam what is your favourite film of
टोटली मैडम व्हाट इज योर फेवरेट फिल्म ऑफ
yourself I
योरसेल्फ
think it would be Tare Zameen Par okay or
आई थिंक इट वुड बी तारे जमी पर ओके या
Tare Zameen Par 3 Idiots dos two and I mean
तारे जमी पर थ्री इडियट्स दोस टू एंड आई
Lagaan is no less no Lagaan is no less
मीन लगान इज नो लेस नो लगान इज नो लेस
Dangal is great Dangal is great or Sarfarosh is
दंगल इज ग्रेट दंगल इज ग्रेट या सरफरोश इज़
very good Sarfarosh Sarfarosh
वैरी गुड सरफरोश
Sarfarosh is the one with Naseeruddin sir ji
सरफरोश इस द वन विद नसरुद्दीन सर जी जी
in which you are a police officer I am an IPS
जिसमें आप पुलिस ऑफिसर हो मैं आईपीएस
officer or right right yes why do you think if so
ऑफिसर या राइट राइट यस व्हाई डू यू थिंक
people will remember Tare Zameen Par or
इफ से पीपल विल रिमेंबर तारे जमीन पर ऑर
for that matter Andaz Apna Apna and your
फॉर दैट मैटर अंदाज अपना-अपना एंड योर
favourite movie Tare Zameen Par why do you you you you
फेवरेट मूवी तारे जमीन पर व्हाई डू यू यू
think is that difference what is
यू यू यू यू थिंक इज दैट डिफरेंस व्हाट इज
the audience looking for versus what you
दी ऑडियंस लुकिंग फॉर वर्सेस व्हाट यू
looking for in a movie the reason
लुकिंग फॉर इन अ मूवी द रीज़न अमोंग्स
Amongst my films I mean it is very difficult
अमोंग्स माय फिल्म्स आई मीन दे इट्स वैरी
most toh main pehle bolo yaar it is
डिफिकल्ट सबसे तो मैं पहले बोलूं यार इट्स
very difficult for me to choose
वैरी डिफिकल्ट फॉर मी टू चूज
but if I have to choose one then I would choose Tare
बट इफ आई हैव टू चूज़ वन देन आई वुड चूज़
Zameen Par simply because of the kind of
तारे जमी पर सिंपली बिकॉज़ ऑफ़ द काइंड ऑफ़
impact it has on the head.  Tare Zameen Par three years
इंपैक्ट इट हेड। तारे जमी पर थ्री इयर्स
have a very deep impact on the society.  Helped a
है वैरी डीप इंपैक्ट ऑन सोसाइटी। हेल्पड अ
lot of kids.  The lives of many children
लॉट ऑफ़ किड्स। बहुत सारे बच्चों की लाइफ
changed.  Parents' lives changed.
चेंज हो गई। पेरेंट्स की लाइफ चेंज हो गई।
And so that's why I told him a lot about I,
और तो इसलिए मैं उसको बहुत आई आई दैट्स
that's why I think it's a special film for me.
व्हाई आई इट्स अ स्पेशल फिल्म फॉर मी।
Ok.  It was able to help a lot of people.
ओके। इट वास एबल टू हेल्प अ लॉट ऑफ पीपल।
Interesting.  Yes.  Do me your favor.  Hmm
इंटरेस्टिंग। हां। डू मी योर फेवर। हम्म
explain
एक्सप्लेन
the story the plot of Sitare Zameen Par without giving it away give people a bite
द स्टोरी द प्लॉट ऑफ सितारे जमीन पर
yes well it's really a story about
हां वेल इट्स इट्स रियली अ स्टोरी अबाउट
Tare Zameen Par which is the exact opposite of
तारे जमी पर का एक्जेक्टली ऑपोजिट है जो
my character ok Nikum was very
मेरा किरदार है ओके निकुम वास वैरी
sensitive
सेंसिटिव
Gulshan is very insensitive he is a rude type of
गुलशन इज वेरी इनसेंसिटिव बदतमीज टाइप का
man he is quarrelsome he gets angry
आदमी है झगड़ालू है गुस्सा आ जाता है
quickly I feel that I am always right he
जल्दी मुझे लगता है हमें मैं ही हमेशा सही
hits the police car after drinking alcohol
हूं पुलिस की गाड़ी ठोक देता है दारू पी
and asks them is there any place to
के और उन्हीं को कहता है कहीं कोई जगह है
park his vehicle.  So it is always right, it
पार्क करने की। तो ही इज़ ऑलवेज राइट ही
feels that way.  So that's kind of the character and
फील्स। तो उस किस्म का कैरेक्टर है एंड
it's really the story of how he gets this
इट्स रियली द स्टोरीज ऑफ़ हाउ व्हेन ही
punishment actually to teach
गेट्स दिस जो पनिशमेंट एक्चुअली टू टीच
basketball to a team of players with
बास्केटबॉल टू अ टीम ऑफ़ प्लेयर्स विद
intellectual disabilities.
इंटेलेक्चुअल डिसेबिलिटीज़।
So, in those three-four months when he is
तो वो तीन-चार महीनों में उनको जब
teaching him basketball, he actually
बास्केटबॉल सिखा रहा है एक्चुअली वो उसको
teaches him to be a good person.  Hum That's the
अच्छा इंसान बनना सिखाते हैं। हम दैट्स द
crux of the film Interesting Or in Tare
क्रक्स ऑफ़ द फिल्म इंटरेस्टिंग या तो तारे
Zameen Par the teacher helps the child.
जमी पर में टीचर ने बच्चे को हेल्प किया
In this, the neuro divergent lot of
था। इसमें जो न्यूरो डायवर्जेंट लॉट ऑफ
players improve the coach.
प्लेयर्स प्लेयर्स हैं वो कोच को सुधारते
Interests bring changes in his life.
हैं। इंटरेस्ट उसकी जिंदगी में बदलाव लाते
Hmm it's the opposite of that.  So, it's
हैं। हम् इट्स अ ऑपोजिट ऑफ़ दैट। सो, इट्स
almost like its humor.  Well it's
ऑलमोस्ट लाइक इट्स ह्यूमर। अच्छा इट्स
Peremyper was very emotional.  Yes.  This is
पेरेमीपर वास् वेरी इमोशनल। यस। दिस इज
very humorous.  Humor is the vehicle.
वेरी ह्यूमरस। ह्यूमर इज द व्हीकल।
Are you saying that this is primarily a comedy?
आर यू सेइंग दैट दिस इज़ प्राइमरली कॉमेडी?
Yes.  Well it's a comedy film.  Ya ya
यस। अच्छा इट्स अ कॉमेडी फिल्म। या या
it's a light hearted film like a Raju
इट्स अ लाइट हार्टेड फिल्म लाइक अ राजू
Irani genre.  good OK.  He uses humor.  What
ईरानी जॉनर। अच्छा ओके। वो ह्यूमर यूज़
he is saying is very
करते हैं। वो जो बात कह रहे हैं वो बहुत
important.  Like in 3
इम्पोर्टेन्ट कह रहे हैं। लाइक इन थ्री
idiots.  But he uses humor as a vehicle
इडियट्स। बट ही यूजस ह्यूमर एज अ व्हीकल
to tell you.  That is the genre.  A very
टू टेल यू। दैट इज द जॉनर। अ वैरी
interesting this owner.  Ok.
इंटरेस्टिंग दिस ओनर। ओके।
Ok why
ओके
no OTT with sitare zameen par yaar
व्हाई नो ओटीटी विद सितारे जमीन पर यार
if I tell you to buy this glass from me
अगर मैं आपसे कहूं कि ये ग्लास आप मुझसे
and I want to sell it so you
खरीदें और मैं ये बेचना चाह रहा हूं आप
buy it from me and if I tell you that if you don’t
मुझसे खरीदें और अगर मैं आपसे कहूं कि आप
buy it then I will come and drop it at your home
अगर नहीं खरीदते हो तो मैं आपके घर पे आके
after 8 weeks for which
ड्रॉप कर लूंगा हम 8 हफ्ते बाद जिसके लिए
you don’t have to pay any extra money then
आपको कोई एक्स्ट्रा पैसा नहीं देना है हम
why would you buy it from me I do
तो आप फिर क्यों खरीदोगे मुझसे मुझे लगता
n’t think any other product in the world would be
नहीं कि दुनिया में और कोई भी प्रोडक्ट इस
sold in this model.
मॉडल में बिकता होगा।
We are the only ones that do this.  Right?
हम इकलौते हैं जो हम ऐसा करते हैं। राइट?
So it does make sense to me.  Good.  And so
सो इट डस मेक सेंस टू मी। अच्छा। एंड सो
once the theatrical release of Sitare Zameen Par is
वंस द थिएटिकल रिलीज ऑफ़ सितारे जमीन पर इज़
over there is no other way to watch it than that.
ओवर देयर इज़ नो अदर वे टू वाच इट देन।
Let's see well let's see you make the decision when it comes.
लेट्स सी अच्छा लेट सी यू यू मेक द डिसजन
When it comes.  Right now
व्हेन इट कम्स। व्हेन इट कम्स। राइट नाउ
I am focusing only on theatres.  I was
आई एम फोकसिंग ओनली ऑन थिएटर्स। आई वास
doing my research and I found that
डूइंग माय रिसर्च एंड आई फाउंड दैट
for this movie you were offered quite a bit
इस मूवी के लिए यू वर ऑफर्ड क्वाइट अ बिट
of money from not just OTTs but studios
ऑफ़ मनी फ्रॉम नॉट जस्ट ओटीटी बट स्टूडियोज
etc and you had this idea that I will
एटसेट्रा एंड यू हैड दिस थिंक कि मैं इसे
make it myself and like you rejected the
खुद बनाऊंगा और लाइक यू रिजेक्टेड द
OTTs,
ओटीटीस
is there any other specific reason why you would do
इज देयर एनी अदर स्पेसिफिक रीज़न व्हाई यू
that or it's just that you wanted
वुड डू दैट या इट्स जस्ट दैट यू वांटेड
creative control as no I just feel it's the
क्रिएटिव कंट्रोल एज नो आई जस्ट फील इट्स
wrong way to release a film.  Well or you
रोंग वे टू रिलीज़ अ फिल्म | अच्छा या यू
just feel it's not the right way to
जस्ट फील इट्स अ डिफिटेस्ट नॉट द राइट वे
release a film.  It's not it's you're
टू टू रिलीज़ अ फिल्म। इट्स नॉट इट्स यू आर
not being fair to the material.  So much hard work has
नॉट बीइंग फेयर टू द मटेरियल। इतनी मेहनत
gone into the film.  I am
गई है फिल्म के अंदर आप उसको। आई आई एम
not comfortable with that.  Got it.  So now,
नॉट कम्फर्टेबल विथ दैट। गॉट इट। तो अब
I am not criticising anyone for whom I work.
जिन-जिन के लिए वर्क मैं किसी को
It works
क्रिटिसाइज नहीं कर रहा हूं। इट वर्क्स
for a lot of people and I appreciate that.
फॉर अ लॉट ऑफ़ पीपल एंड आई अप्रिशिएट दैट।
Right.  Doesn't work for me, so I don't want to do that.
राइट। डजंट वर्क फॉर मी, सो आई डोंट वांट
Hmm.  I have full
टू डू दैट। हम्म। आई हैव फुल
you know, I have full loyalty for the theatres
यू नो, आई हैव फुल लॉयल्टी फॉर द थिएटर्स
in the cinema halls.  I feel it's a very
इन द सिनेमा हॉल। आई फील इट्स अ वैरी
different way of
डिफरेंट वे ऑफ़
connecting with a film, a little sorry sorry
कनेक्टिंग विद अ फिल्म थोड़ा सॉरी सॉरी
no sir, yes sorry, so what is it, when we
नहीं सर हां सॉरी तो क्या है हम जब फिल्म
watch a film, there should be some enjoyment in it,
देखते हैं तो उसका एक मजा भी होना चाहिए
you sit in a dark theatre,
आप अंधेरे अंधेरे थिएटर में बैठते हैं
on a big screen, the way you
बड़े से स्क्रीन पे आप जिस तरह से आप
connect is probably in an
कनेक्ट करते हैं वो शायद
experience, here bells are ringing
इन एन एक्सपीरियंस यहां घंटियां भी बज रही
and notifications are also coming, so
हैं और नोटिफिकेशंस भी आ रहे हैं तो उसमें
what film will you watch in that, so for me you know it's
आप क्या फिल्म देखोगे तो मेरे लिए यू नो
really great to watch a film in the
इट्स रियली ग्रेट टू टू वॉच अ फिल्म इन द
darkness of a theatre where you are, that's the
डार्कनेस ऑफ़ अ थिएटर वेयर यू आर दैट्स द
best way to watch a film.  No I would even say so
बेस्ट वे टू वाच फिल्म। नो आई वुड इवन से
much as it's super difficult to watch anything
सो मच एज़ इट्स सुपर डिफिकल्ट टू वॉच
long form because my phone is ringing.
एनीथिंग लॉन्ग फॉर्म बिकॉज़ मेरा फोन बज
I just received my food order.
रहा है। अभी मेरे को मेरा खाने का आर्डर आ
Right now my friend is saying that you
गया। अभी मेरा दोस्त कह रहा है कि तू
come online, we will play a game.  What do I do and
ऑनलाइन आजा गेम खेलेंगे। क्या मैं क्या
how do I focus?  How can I focus on my studies
कैसे फोकस करूं मैं? मैं पढ़ाई पे कैसे
?  But movies are still secondary for me.
फोकस करूं? मैं मूवीज़ तो फिर भी सेकेंडरी
You focus on anything.  How do
हैं। किसी चीज़ पे भी आप फोकस। कैसे फोकस
I focus?  This is a real problem.  And this real
करूं? ये एक रियल प्रॉब्लम है। और ये रियल
problem is an issue for all of us.  Right?  So I
प्रॉब्लम हम सबका इशू है। राइट? सो आई
completely agree.  Or to
कंप्लीटली एग्री। या अ
watch it in a theatre, one thing I have a lot
थिएटर में देखने की जो एक तो आई हैव अ लॉट
of loyalty for cinema halls and theatres
ऑफ़ लॉयल्टी फॉर सिनेमा हॉल्स एंड थिएटर्स
and I have faith in my audience and if the
एंड आई हैव फेथ इन माय ऑडियंस याह अगर
film is made well then they will come to
फिल्म अच्छी बनी है तो फिर वो आएंगे थिएटर
watch it in the theatre, yes I believe that who is he is
में देखने हां आई बिलीव दैट हु इज इज इज
your best friend
इज इज इज इज इज इज इज इज योर बेस्ट फ्रेंड
in the industry, oh I have got a lot of
इन द इंडस्ट्री ओह आई हैव गॉट अ लॉट ऑफ़
good friends, okay good friends, very good
गुड फ्रेंड्स ओके गुड फ्रेंड्स वैरी गुड
friends, or Ranbir Ranveer Anil Kapoor, Jackie
फ्रेंड्स या रणबीर रणवीर अनिल कपूर जैकी
Salman Shahrukh, okay or
सलमान शाहरुख ओके अ या
and would you talk about when you guys hang
एंड वुड यू टॉक अबाउट व्हेन यू गाइस हैंग
out in cinema,
आउट सिनेमा
I saw some video of Ranbir being at your
आई सॉ सम वीडियो ऑफ़ रणबीर बीइंग एट योर
place and then recently, yes walking in,
प्लेस एंड देन अभी रिसेंटली हां वाकिंग इन
those stars were very excited to
वो तो सितारे बहुत एक्साइटेड हो गए थे
see him, actually I did for
उनको देखने के लिए एक्चुअली आई डिड फॉर
them because this is his first film.  These 10
देम बिकॉज़ ये उनकी पहली फिल्म है। दीज़ 10
actors who are neuro divergent.  Right right right right
एक्टर्स हु आर न्यूरो डायवर्जेंट। राइट
right.  So this is a
राइट राइट राइट राइट। तो उनके लिए यह एक
very special occasion for them so I want to
बहुत ही खास मौका है जो तो आई वांट टू गिव
give them the best.  Got it, got it, got it.  So,
देम द बेस्ट। गॉट इट, गॉट इट, गॉट इट। तो,
he wants to meet Ranbir.  So,
वह रणबीर को मिलना चाहते हैं। तो,
actually I surprised them.  They did not know that
एक्चुअली आई सरप्राइज़ देम। उनको पता नहीं
Ranbir was coming, Sachin was coming.
था रणबीर आने वाला है, सचिन आने वाला है।
Got it.  They didn't know that.  So let them
गॉट इट। दे डिडन्ट नो दैट। सो दे वर
thrill.  Yes.  And like I am keeping the premiere on the 18th.
थ्रिल्ड। हां। और जैसे 18 को मैं प्रीमियर
I get very irritated at premieres.
रख रहा हूं। मुझे प्रीमियर्स में बहुत
Why?  Hey, it is very difficult to
कोफ्त होती है। क्यों? अरे, बड़ा मुश्किल
organize and then I am
होता है ऑर्गेनाइज करना और फिर मैं होस्ट
playing the host.  When all my seniors are coming,
प्ले कर रहा हूं। सब मेरे सीनियर आ रहे
I get very tensed.  Center of
हैं तो, मुझे बड़ी टेंशन होती है। सेंटर ऑफ
attention.  No, I am not the centre of attention, there is a
अटेंशन। नहीं सेंटर ऑफ़ अटेंशन नहीं
lot of responsibility that day, friend.
रिसोंसिबिलिटी बहुत होती है उस दिन यार।
Well but I am doing it for them because
अच्छा बट इनके लिए मैं कर रहा हूं बिकॉज़
I feel it would be really exciting for them.
आई फील इट बी रियली एक्साइटिंग फॉर देम।
Or they will get to meet the whole industry and
या दे विल गेट टू मीट द होल इंडस्ट्री एंड
you know then they will be the stars on that
यू नो देन दे विल बी द स्टार्स ऑन दैट
evening right so I want to do it for them.
इवनिंग राइट सो आई वांट टू डू इट फॉर देम।
got got it got it got it.   Do
गॉट गॉट इट गॉट इट गॉट इट।
you still play chess?  Once in a while or are
डू यू स्टिल प्ले चेस? वंस इन अ वाइल या
you amazed with what is happening to India and Indian
या यू अब्रेस्ड विद हाउ इंडिया और इंडियन
chess?  Do you have any ideas
चेस के साथ क्या हो रहा है? कुछ आईडिया
?  I keep track of it a little bit.  These days I am
आपको? थोड़ा बहुत मैं ट्रैक रखता हूं। आजकल
very engrossed in films so I do
फिल्म में ज्यादा घुसा हुआ हूं तो आई डोंट
n't keep track of anything actually.  Right.  You
कीप ट्रैक ऑफ़ एनीथिंग एक्चुअली। राइट। यू
know that world champion is now Indian.
नो दैट वर्ल्ड चैंपियन इज नाउ इंडियन।
Gokesh is now become world champion?  Yes
गोकेश इस नाउ बिकम वर्ल्ड चैंपियन? हां
sir.  When was this?  This is how many
सर। व्हेन व्हेन वास् दिस? दिस इज़ हाउ
months ago?  four five months ago just
मेनी मंथ्स अगो? फोर फाइव मंथ्स एगो अभी
in classical style classical style.  And
इन क्लासिकल स्टाइल क्लासिकल स्टाइल। एंड
so Magnis basically said I won't play
सो मतलब मैग्निस बेसिकली सेड मैं खेलूंगा
anymore.  So that's why I did
नहीं अब मैं तो। तो ही डिडन्ट प्ले दैट
n't play that tournament.  No.  He didn't play that.   he
टूर्नामेंट ना। ना। ही डिडन्ट प्ले दैट।
gave up.  Yes.  And even the Candidates
ही गिवेन अप। हां। एंड इवन द कैंडिडेट्स
run before he entered the World Championship
रन बिफोर ही एंटर्ड द वर्ल्ड चैंपियनशिप
was phenomenal from Gokesh.  And then I mean
वाज़ फिनोमिनल फ्रॉम गोकेश। एंड देन मतलब
sir as somebody who grows up playing chess I am so
सर एज समबडी हु ग्रो प्लेइंग चेस आई एम सो
proud where India is set to chess and I
प्राउड वेयर इंडिया इज़ सेट टू चेस एंड आई
make it a point that I mention this
मेक इट अ पॉइंट कि मैं इसको मेंशन करूं
because people don't realise the kind of
बिकॉज़ पीपल डोंट रियलाइज़ द काइंड ऑफ़
dominance India has on chess is the kind of
डोमिनेंस इंडिया हैज़ ऑन चेस इज़ द काइंड ऑफ़
dominance India has on cricket.  That's
डोमिनेंस इंडिया हैज़ ऑन क्रिकेट। दैट्स
right.  This happened at this time.  Yes.  And it's
राइट। इस वक्त ऐसा हो गया। हां। एंड इट्स
only going to get better because I
ओनली गोइंग टू गेट बेटर बिकॉज़ अगर मैं नाम
start naming under 20-21 years old
लेना शुरू करूं ना अंडर 20- 21 इयर्स ओल्ड
chess players who are top 20 already.  It
चेस प्लेयर्स हु आर टॉप 20 ऑलरेडी। इट
just doesn't end.  It's just India.  ya ya
जस्ट डजंट एंड। इट्स जस्ट इंडिया। या या
just no.  I think lots of young kids in
जस्ट नो। आई थिंक लॉट ऑफ यंग किड्स इन
India have taken up chess.  I think Anand
इंडिया हैव टेकन टू चेस। आई थिंक ये आनंद
also had a big hand in this.  These are these are
का भी इसमें बड़ा हाथ था। दी आर दीज़ आर
wishes kids.  Or, or, or.  This is she's
विशिस किड्स। या, या, या। दिस इज शीस
kids.  Or.  His impact is 1:1
किड्स। या। हिज इंपैक्ट 1:1
and I mean I started playing in the
एंड आई मीन आई स्टार्टेड प्लेइंग इन द
light of Anand becoming world champion.
लाइट ऑफ आनंद बिकमिंग वर्ल्ड चैंपियन।
Because he infiltrates the culture,
बिकॉज़ वो इनफिल्ट्रेट करता है ना कल्चर को
everybody is like, hey this is the Indian chess
एवरीबडी इस लाइक कि अरे ये इंडियन चेस
champion, this that.  And I remember seeing
चैंपियन दिस दैट। एंड आई रिमेंबर सीइंग
him for the first time.  I was like be
हिम फॉर द फर्स्ट टाइम। आई वाज लाइक बी
nine and 10 hero moment.  hero.  Hey amazing
नाइन और 10 हीरो मोमेंट। हीरो। ही अमेजिंग
cow.  Or, I am sure sir.  I never
गाय। या, आई एम श्योर सर। मैं मेरी कभी
met him again after that.  But hero
मुलाकात उसके बाद नहीं हुई। बट हीरो
moment and now we are seeing what one man
मोमेंट एंड नाउ वी आर सीइंग व्हाट वन मैन
can do for the rest of the country.  Hmm.
कैन डू फॉर द रेस्ट ऑफ़ द कंट्री। हम्।
It's incredible.  As a fin.  Or are you
इट्स इनक्रेडिबल। एज अ फिन। या या आर यू
philosophical and spiritual about life?  Do
फिलोसोफिकल और स्पिरिचुअल अबाउट लाइफ? डू
you believe in God?
यू बिलीव इन गॉड?
Actually release religion I feel it's a
एक्चुअली रिलीज रिलीजन आई फील ना इट्स अ
very personal thing.  Hmm for people.  So I
वैरी पर्सनल थिंग। हम्म फॉर पीपल। सो आई
try and not talk about it on public
आई ट्राई एंड नॉट टॉक अबाउट इट ऑन पब्लिक
platforms.  I get it.  But are you
प्लेटफॉर्म्स। आई गेट इट। बट आर यू
spiritual?  I think so.  Hmm.  I think
स्पिरिचुअल? आई थिंक सो। हम्म। आई थिंक
so.  Do you meditate?  I do.  Or.  what
सो। डू यू मेडिटेट? आई डू। या। व्हाट
type?
टाइप?
Well I had been to Vipassana which I had to
वेल आई हैड बीन टू विपासना व्हिच आई हैड
cut shot after four days my eye I lost
टू कट शॉट आफ्टर फोर डेज माय आई आई लॉस्ट
my friend actually a very close friend my
माय फ्रेंड एक्चुअली वैरी क्लोज फ्रेंड
mind passed away so I had to go on a boat on the
माइंड पास्ड अवे सो आई हैड टू अ बोट ऑन द
fourth night
फोर्थ नाईट
but those four days really had a deep impact
बट दैट फोर डेज रियली हैड अ डीप इंपैक्ट
on me.  It's like a boot camp for
ऑन मी | इट्स लाइक अ बूट कैंप फॉर
meditation or I have done Vipassana twice or you have done it twice
मेडिटेशन या आई हैव डन विपसना ट्वाइस ओ यू
and I feel like it is a factory
हैव ट्वाइसर एंड मेरे को लगता है फैक्ट्री
reset of life when life goes out of hand, I
रिसेट है लाइफ का जब लाइफ हाथ से बाहर चली
sit there for 10 days and
जाए 10 दिन जाके बैठा हूं हम और आदमी अपने
all the ghosts inside me from which the man is running away, come back.
अंदर के सारे भूत जिनसे भाग रहा है ना सब
Nothing is left behind.  Hum and
आ जाते हैं। कुछ नहीं छूटता पीछे। हम एंड
I think I have also read as much as Goenka ji says in
आई थिंक मैंने जितने आल्सो गोयंका जी की
his lectures.
जो बातें होती हैं जो वो लेक्चर देते हैं
Superb no agenda.  Or there is no
टॉप। सुपर्ब नो एजेंडा। या कोई उसमें
irrelevant thing mixed in it.  There's no
इधर-उधर की बात मिक्स नहीं है। कोई
mixing up of messaging here and there.
इधर-उधर का मैसेजिंग मिक्स नहीं है। सिंपल
Focus on simple techniques.  If it works then sit, if it does
टेक्निक पे फोकस करो। काम करे तो बैठना,
n't work then leave.  That's it.  Hm but
नहीं करे तो चले जाना। दैट्स इट। हम बट
for a lot of my psychological unwellness hm
फॉर अ लॉट ऑफ़ माय साइकोलॉजिकल अनवेलनेस हम
Vipana has been a panacea when my mind goes out of
हम विपना हैज़ बीन अ रामबाण जब मेरा दिमाग
my hands and I cannot control it,
मेरे हाथ से निकल जाता है और काबू में
I go and sit in
नहीं आता ना मैं जाके बैठ जाता हूं
meditation, yes yes sir and in 10 days it
मेडिटेशन हां हां सर और वो 10 दिन में ऐसा
happens that some doctor
होता है कि किसी डॉक्टर ने आत्मा के अंदर
takes out the whole soul from inside it and now you can see it still exists, it's not that it does
से निकाल ली सारी एंड नाउ यू कैन सी इट इट
not exist
स्टिल एक्सिस्ट ऐसा नहीं है कि वो नहीं है
but you can see that this is a disease, hey it was
बट आप देख सकते हो अच्छा ये बीमारी है अरे
not being caught at all, it was making me wander, was chasing it away, you know that
पकड़ में ही नहीं आ रही थी घुमा रही थी भगा
starts happening, no
रही थी यू नो दैट्स स्टार्ट्स हैपनिंग नो
meditation I think is it something
मेडिटेशन आई थिंक इज अ
really amazing or I have one
इट्स समथिंग रियली अमेजिंग या आई हैव वन
last question we
लास्ट क्वेश्चन हम
look into the camera and say something to young Aamir
लुक इन द कैमरा एंड से समथिंग टू यंग आमिर
as an advice oh or it's a new one, what
एज एन एडवाइस ओह या इट्स अ न्यू वन क्या
advice should I give you friend that whatever
एडवाइस दूं यार
mistakes you have made are good,
जो जो गलतियां आपने की है अच्छी अच्छी हैं
do them again,
दोबारा करिएगा
right because only by making those mistakes will you reach here.   By
राइट क्योंकि वो गलतियां करके ही आप यहां
learning from those mistakes.  Got it.  Got it.
उन गलतियों से सीख के। गॉट इट। गोट इट।
well sir.  We have to cut this shot.  You be on a
वेल सर। वी हैव टू कट दिस शॉट। यू बी ऑन अ
very busy tour.  Thank you so much.  Lovely
वैरी बिज़ी टूर। थैंक यू सो मच। लवली
meeting you and chatting with you here.  I hope
मीटिंग यू एंड चैटिंग विथ यू हियर। आई होप
so sir.  I hope I got you at the fact.  You
सो सर। आई होप आय गॉट यू एट द फैक्ट। यु
lovely energy.  Thank you sir.  If you ever need another
लवली एनर्जी। थैंक यू सर। इफ यू एवर नीड
person to talk to you.  I am here.
अनदर पर्सन टू टॉक टू यू। आई ऍम हियर।
Offering my.  But thank you so much for your
ऑफरिंग माई। बट थैंक यू सो मच फॉर योर
time.  This is absolute pleasure and an
टाइम। दिस इज़ अब्सोल्यूट प्लेजर एंड एन
absolute fan moment for me.  Almost never
अब्सोलुट फैन मोमेंट फॉर मी। ऑलमोस्ट नेवर
happened on this show.  I meet with lots of
हैपेंड ऑन दिस शो। आई मेंट विथ लॉट ऑफ
people.  I'm very real.  That Star Stuck.
पीपल। आई एम वैरी रेली। दैट स्टार स्टक।
Thank you.  Thank you for your wonderful art.
थैंक यू। थैंक यू फॉर योर वंडरफुल आर्ट।
Thank you for impacting me in all the right
थैंक यू फॉर इम्पैक्टिंग मी ऑल द राइट
ways.  Thank you for Satyamev Jayate.  Three
वेज। थैंक यू फॉर सत्यमेव जयते। थ्री
Years Tare Zameen Par Lagaan and all the other
इयर्स तारे जमीन पर लगान एंड ऑल द अदर
great working.  Thank you for your own style.
ग्रेट वर्किंग। थैंक यू फॉर अंदाज
Thank you.
थैंक यू।